Prologue
Two small pairs of boots echoed on the afternoon
cobblestones—one pair in a sprint, the other
in a stumble and slide. A blond girl, no older
than five, dragged a raven-haired girl an
inch taller and a year older down the sea
lane toward a small cottage.
The dark-haired girl’s lungs were sputtering,
each inhale a failure.
She was drowning on dry land.
As the house came into view, the blond girl
opened her mouth to scream for help but before
any sound could come out, the other girl’s
mother burst through the door. Like she knew
what had happened—she always seemed to know
what they’d done.
“Evie!” the mother cried, cradling her
daughter in a heap at her chest and running
toward the cottage. “Anna,” she said to
the little blonde, who was panting from carrying
her friend so far, “fetch the royal physician—”
“But—”
“Go!”
The girl didn’t protest again, fine boots
clacking against the cobblestones as she regained
speed.
When her mother shut the cottage door tightly
behind them, the raven-headed girl knew the
physician’s medicine wouldn’t heal her.
Only one thing would.
“Gianni!” The mother called, and the girl’s
father poked his head out of the bedroom,
his face slack with the sleep he wasn’t
allowed on his latest whaling trip.
“Evie . . . what—”
“A broken rib. Maybe a punctured lung.”
She laid the girl in her bed and ripped the
girl’s bodice to her navel. Blood under
the skin showed black across the expanse of
the little girl’s ribs, fissures like spiderwebs
crossed from spine to sternum. The mother
tried to read her daughter’s dark eyes.
“What happened?”
The girl licked her lips before inhaling just
enough air to speak.
“I saved Nik.”
That was true. And the little girl was proud.
Daring to smile despite the pain.
They’d spent the morning together—the
blonde, the raven-haired girl, and their boy—running
through the waves, climbing rocks, dancing
in the sand. But then the afternoon came and
it was time for them to part. The boy sent
back to his castle, the little girls home—the
younger one to her mansion, ten times the
size of the other girl’s tiny cottage.
Mischievous and sunburnt, they ran in protest,
the boy leading the way, holding the girls’
hands as they raced across the stepping-stone
rocks that led into the cove. They giggled
and shrieked as they hopped from rock to rock,
the boy’s minder chiding them from the shore.
But one rock was slick with moss. The boy
slipped—falling backward, the base of his
skull aimed directly at a crook of solid stone.
In a blink, the little girl made her choice.
She threw her body between the boy and the
jagged edge of the rock. Her back took the
hit with a huge crack. Her head snapped back,
her skull missing impact by a hair. Just as
she hit, the boy’s head bounced onto the
pilled cotton of her bodice rather than smashing
into the rock.
It was a thing of magic that she’d made
it in time.
They were caught then. The boy’s minder
yanked them back onto the beach and told them
in stern tones to never do that again. Then
the old woman hauled the boy away without
a good-bye, leaving the girls on the sand.
As they turned for home, the little raven-haired
girl stumbled, the shock wearing off and the
pain beginning. It radiated up her back, around
her rib cage, to the front of her dress. She
couldn’t catch her breath, each inhale stopping
short. The little blonde said she’d walk
her friend home but by the time they made
it to the sea lane, the raven-headed girl
couldn’t stand, all her weight on the blonde’s
shoulders.
“Oh, Evie . . . ,” the girl’s mother
said. As if she’d seen it all. Immediately,
she sent her husband for her bottles. Her
inks. Not that one. This one. She laid the
girl in her bed and lit a fire with a snap
of her fingers.
And tried every healing spell she knew.
It only took seconds to know none of them
would work. The girl’s breath withered until
it was almost nothing at all.
The mother wept, wishing for her sister—the
strongest witch. Healer of Kings, reviving
those in power who turn a blind eye to magic
when their lives depend on it, but banish
it when it doesn’t. She was the reason the
physician might come at all—though he would
be too late. As would Hansa, a day away, healing
yet another noble.
The girl’s father pressed his hand into
his wife’s shoulder and wiped away her tears.
Then he squeezed his daughter’s hand, already
growing cold, her circulation failing.
“I’ll go fetch the minister—”
“Not yet,” the mother said, determination
ringing in her voice. The girl’s mother
stood at the edge of the bed, her shoulders
now pin straight, her voice calm and direct.
“There is one more spell I can try.”
With gentle fingers, she painted octopus ink
across the little girl’s cheeks, down her
neck, and across her chest. Then her mother
laid her hands gently over the girl’s chest.
“Don’t you worry, Evie.”
The words she said next were old and dark,
and the little girl didn’t understand them.
They made her blood crackle like the fire
across the room. Stole the air from the cottage.
Made her mother shake, violently, as she held
her hands to her daughter’s skin.
The little girl couldn’t do anything but
watch her mother, her veins singing. Soon,
her mother’s palms on her skin became more
than damp. They began to burn.
And then the pain stopped. Air rushed into
the little girl’s lungs, and her chest rose.
She exhaled, long and deep.
At that the girl’s mother smiled—just
before her own body began to seize, her eyes
rolling back in her head.
It was too much. The mother’s chest compressed,
a long breath pushing out—but no inhale
following.
“Greta! Greta!” The girl’s father placed
his hands on his wife’s face, his palms
burning and flying away, suddenly red.
The prickle in the little girl’s blood spiked
with fear. She struggled to pull herself to
sit, her mother’s hands sliding away as
her form slumped over and her pale cheek smashed
into the bedsheet. The little girl didn’t
hesitate, reaching for her mother’s potions.
She turned her mother’s head to face upward
before smearing ink across those pale cheeks,
her little fingers blistering with the touch.
Her own skin was pink and warm and full of
life as her mother’s skin turned as white
as snow, as hot as ash.
The girl was smart, though. She’d watched
her mother enough. She knew how these spells
worked. Magic was barter—the right words,
actions, potions for the right result.
She put her hands on her mother’s face and
began repeating those strange words.
Words of life.
“Evelyn, no!” Her father didn’t move,
just screamed, fear freezing him to his spot
at the foot of the bed.
But the little girl had fumbled her way through
the words enough that her own skin began to
grow hot. The pain returned. Her breath became
shallow. Then her mother’s eyes flew open,
showing beautiful hazel instead of the whites.
It was working.
Her father looked from his wife to his daughter.
Those words were dark. Old. Powerful. He knew
this as much as he knew his native tongue.
Her mother’s lips began moving. She took
a deep breath. “Gefa!” With this single
command, she stole the words right from the
little girl’s mouth. Dark words and dark
magic and all sound gone from the girl’s
powerful tongue.
Still, the child kept going, chest heaving—she
was yelling but could not be heard. Tears
as dark as night flowed down her little cheeks.
Black coating her vision, the girl began to
wail without sound, her whole body shaking.
And, with her last wisp of energy, the girl’s
mother looked to her father.
“Bring Hansa home. Tell her. Promise.”
As he nodded, her mother whispered one last
spell, and the little girl’s screams filled
the air, black tears dripping onto her ruined
dress.
“No, Mama, no!”
The little girl grabbed her mother’s hand,
still burning to the touch, and saw the light
flee from her hazel eyes.
THE SEA IS A FICKLE WITCH.
She is just as likely to bestow a kiss as
to steal the breath from your lips. Beautiful
and cruel, and every glimmering wrinkle in
between. Filling our bellies and our coffers
when she is generous. Coolly watching as we
don black and add tears to her waters when
she is wicked.
Only the tide follows her moods—giving and
taking at the same salty rate.
Still, she is more than our witch—she’s
our queen.
In all her spells and tantrums, she is one
of us. The crown jewel of Havnestad, nuzzled
against our shores—for better or worse.
Tonight, dressed in her best party finery,
she appears calm, anger buried well below
her brilliant surface. Still, there’s a
charge in the air as the stars wink with the
coming summer solstice and the close of Nik’s
sixteenth birthday.
Formally: Crown Prince Asger Niklas Bryniulf
Øldenburg III, first in line to the throne
of the sovereign kingdom of Havnestad.
Informally: just Nik.
But “just Nik” isn’t quite right either.
He’s not just anything to me. He’s my
best friend. My only friend, really.
And now he’s dancing with Malvina across
the deck of his father’s grand steamship.
That is, if you can call her violent tossing
and whirling “dancing.” My stomach lurches
as Nik comes within inches of tipping over
the rail after she forces an overenthusiastic
spin. I wish she’d just give it up.
Malvina, formally Komtesse Malvina Christensen,
is a perpetual royal suitor. She and her father
have been vying for King Asger’s attention
for years, hoping he will make the match.
Yet despite Nik’s good-natured patience
for her dancing, I have my doubts there will
be a royal wedding in their future.
I want to look away from the pink silk blur
of Malvina, but Nik’s eyes are begging me
to rescue him. Pleading. Silently calling
my name across the distance—Evvvvvvieee.
I am the only one who can save him. Every
youth in town is here, but no one else can
cut in on a girl like Malvina. For the others,
there would be consequences—lost invitations
to galas, the oldest horse on the weekend
hunt, a seat at the table next to one’s
senile great-tante instead of the Komtesse.
For me, there are none of those things. You
can’t fall far in society if you’re not
part of it to begin with.
After another aggressive turn, I finally stride
onto the makeshift dance floor, ignoring a
chorus of smirks as I go—they’ve seen
this play before. Malvina will be the victim,
I’ll be the villain, and Nik will let it
happen. It can be a messy business, being
the crown prince’s confidante; enduring
small humiliations is only a fraction of the
cost. But I won’t apologize for helping
him. We all make compromises in friendships,
and having Nik’s loyalty when no one else
will even look me in the eye is worth every
criticism I face.
I tap the girl on one sturdy shoulder, screw
my face into exaggerated panic, and point
to the eight-layered, blue-sugar-spackled
monstrosity she insisted on crafting.
“Oh, angels, Evie! What is it?” Malvina
barks.
“The cake’s icing—”
“Fondant,” she corrects, as if I’ve
spit on her oma’s grave.
“The fondant—it’s bulging.”
True panic colors her features as her feet
refuse to move. Torn between dancing with
Nik and rescuing her masterpiece from a bulbous
fate, her eyes skip to my face for a moment,
incredulous. She fears I’ve purposely stolen
her turn. It’s just the sort of thing the
girls of Havnestad think I would do—the
ones whispering in the shadows about us now.
Except in this case, they’re right.
“Do your duty, Malvina. It was lovely dancing
with you.” Nik bends into a slight bow,
royal manners on display, not a hint of displeasure
in his features.
When his eyes cut away, Malvina sneaks a glare
my way, her disdain for me as clear as her
worry that I’m actually telling the truth.
She doesn’t need to say what she’s thinking,
and she won’t—not if she ever wants to
dance with Nik again. So, when Nik completes
his bow, she simply plasters on a trained
smile and leaves him with the most perfect
curtsy before running off in a rush of golden
hair and intent.
Now Nik bows deeply to me as if I’m his
newest suitor, his mop of black hair briefly
obscuring his coal-dark eyes. “May I have
the remainder of this dance, my lady?”
My lips curl into a smile as my legs automatically
dip into a polite curtsy. My lady. Despite
how good those words feel, they’re enough
to earn me the ire of everyone on this boat.
To them I am just the royal fisherman’s
daughter abusing the prince’s kindness,
using him for his station. They won’t believe
we’re just friends, as we’ve always been,
since we were in diapers. Before I knew what
I was and he knew who he was meant to be.
“But of course, Crown Prince Niklas,”
I reply.
He meets my eyes, and we both burst out laughing.
Formality has never worn well between us—regardless
of Nik’s training.
We settle in and begin to waltz across the
deck. He has a good foot on me, but he’s
practiced at leaning in—whispers are often
our most convenient language.
“Took you long enough,” he says, twirling
me through the last bars of the song.
“I wanted to see how long you’d stay dry.”
He gasps with false horror in my ear, a smile
tingeing it. “You’d send your own best
friend swimming with the mermaids on his birthday?”
“I hear they’re beautiful—not a bad
present for a teenage boy.”
“They also prefer their presents not breathing.”
My eyes shoot to his. I can feel the slightest
tremble in my jaw. Today would’ve been our
friend Anna’s birthday too. It still is,
though she is no longer here to celebrate
it. She was exactly a year younger than Nik.
We’d each had our share of close calls in
those days, the great and powerful goddess
Urda seeming to want us all for herself. But
we lost Anna. I glance down, feeling tears
hot against my lash line, even after four
years’ time. Nik sighs and tugs a curl off
my face. He waits until I finally glance up.
There’s a soft smile riding his lips, and
I know he regrets pulling us from a place
of joy to one so fraught. “Well, thank you
for saving me, Evie. As always.”
It’s as good a subject change as any, but
it’s not enough—and we both know it. I
take a deep breath and look over Nik’s shoulder,
not trusting myself to say more. I swallow
and try to concentrate on the party. Everything
here has been borrowed for Nik’s celebration—the
ship, the free-flowing hvidtøl, the band,
two servants, and a coal man—and it’s
beautiful. I focus on the miniature lanterns
ringing the deck, the golden thread of my
single fancy dress catching their glow.
Suddenly, Malvina hoists herself onto the
dessert table, still frantically trying to
control the cake’s growing bulge. I expect
Nik to laugh, or at least knock out a very
royal snort, but instead he’s looking over
my shoulder, portside, at the sea. I follow
his eyes, and my heart sputters to a stop
when I make out a swift schooner, the familiar
line of a boy—a man—adjusting the sail.
“Iker . . .” His name falls from my lips
in a sigh before I can catch it. I meet Nik’s
eyes, a blush crawling up my cheeks. “I
didn’t know he was coming.”
“Neither did I.” He shrugs and raises
a brow. “But Iker’s not exactly one to
confirm an invitation. Missed that day at
prince school. The lecture about being on
time, too.”
“I believe it’s called ‘fashionably
late,’” I say.
“Yes, well, I suppose I wouldn’t know,”
Nik says with a laugh.
The little schooner closes in, and I see that
it’s only Iker—he hasn’t brought a crew
with him from Rigeby Bay, not that I’d expect
him to. He’s a weather-worn fisherman trapped
in a life designed for silk and caviar. He
redirects the mainsail perfectly, his muscles
tensing tightly as he aims straight for his
cousin’s form.
Nik leans to my ear. “There goes my dancing
partner.”
I punch him on the arm. “You don’t know
that.”
“True, but I do know how you’ve looked
at him since my cake had about ten fewer candles
on it.”
I roll my eyes, but I can’t help a smile
creeping up my lips. He’s somewhat right,
though now isn’t the best time to argue
that the way I looked at Iker changed from
brotherly to something else entirely about
four years ago, not ten.
I clear my throat. “I’m sure Malvina won’t
mind—she’s almost finished with your cake,”
I say, nodding in the direction of the blue
monstrosity but never taking my eyes off Iker
as he readies to throw up a line to the steamer.
Nik hugs me close and dips down to my ear.
“You’re such a ravishingly loyal friend.”
“Always have been. Always will be.”
“’Tis true.” Nik grins before waving
a long arm above his head. “Well, if it
isn’t the crown prince of Rigeby Bay!”
“And here I hoped to surprise you,” Iker
says, laughing. “Can’t surprise a lighthouse
of a man on his own boat, I suppose.”
Nik laughs, standing even taller. “Not if
I’m turned the right way.”
Iker laughs even deeper. There is salt in
his hair and few days’ worth of scruff lining
his strong jawline, but he strides across
his deck with the elegance of a prince. He
glances up at me, his eyes briefly betraying
a hint of doubt about the sturdiness of my
frame, but tosses the line to me anyway. I
catch it, securing it with a knot I learned
from Father.
Iker hauls himself up the rope and onto the
ship. He manages to land on the small patch
of deck just between Nik and myself. Behind
us a crowd has gathered.
“Happy birthday, Cousin.” Eyes laughing,
Iker claps Nik on the back and brings him
in for a hug, his toned arms fully encasing
Nik’s spindly-yet-strong form.
When they release, Iker’s eyes go right
to me. They’re the clearest of blues—like
ancient ice in the fjords of the north.
“Evelyn,” he says, still retaining an
air of formality from his upbringing, but
he then shockingly pulls me into a hug.
I freeze, eyes on Nik as he and everyone else
on the ship stares. Iker doesn’t seem to
notice or care and pulls me tighter, his arms
wrapped around my waist. Warm from ship work,
he smells of salt and limes. His shirt is
freckled with water droplets, onyx on the
starched gray fabric—the sea leaving her
mark.
When the moment is over and he lets me go,
an arm lingers across my shoulders. I try
to ignore the question nagging me, the one
I’m sure everyone else is asking too. Why
me? We’ve known each other since we were
children, but he’s never shown me this kind
of affection before. I’m not his type. I’m
not anyone’s type. Yet Iker continues to
act as if it’s all completely normal. He
turns to Nik, to the crowd, and grins that
perfect smile.
“Good people of Havnestad,” he says, his
voice commanding yet sincere. Then the grin
grows wider. “Let’s give the prince a
celebration so hearty, he’ll never forget
it.”
I FEEL AS IF I’M LIVING IN A DREAM.
Still warm from Iker’s strong embrace, I
twirl across the dance floor in his arms.
I tried to tell Iker we shouldn’t, but he
wouldn’t hear of it. “Let them talk,”
Iker said. If only he knew how much they already
did.
I can sense Malvina’s eyes following me.
Yes, Malvina, this is what it looks like when
someone dances without fearing for his life.
But I try not to think about her. I want to
remember this moment, even the smallest details.
Everything about him wears like oiled leather
and loved muslin. His hands are rough and
worn from the sea, and yet they are gentle,
his thumb delicately caressing mine.
My twelve-year-old fantasies were never this
detailed—hardly anything beyond me in a
grand purple gown and Iker in his royal finery
hand-in-hand on a stroll through the palace
gardens. The reality is so different, so intense,
and I’m not sure I’m handling it well.
I know I’m not. Can he feel my palms sweating?
My heart beating loudly against his chest?
“I saw you from my deck, you know,” he
whispers in my ear. “Before coming aboard.
You’ve never looked more beautiful, Evie.
And I’ve never begged the gods to steer
my ship faster.”
I don’t know what to say, my voice seizing
in my throat. I look around instead, trying
to organize my thoughts. The sun has completely
set, the last strands of light gone with our
plates in a rush and clatter of tiny quail
bones, torsk tails, pea pods, and strawberry
hulls. And though the entire ship deck is
still lit by a ring of miniature lanterns,
the remaining shadow is enough that it almost
feels as if we’re alone.
Just a boy, a girl, and the sea.
The song ends and he hugs me tight. When he
pulls back, he runs his fingers along my jawbone.
“I shouldn’t have stayed away from Havnestad
so long,” he says, capturing one of my curls
between his fingers. “You have the same
hair you did as a child.” His gaze lifts
to mine. “The same starry-night eyes.”
I struggle not to look down—down to where
he’s still wound a lock of my hair lightly
between his fingers. I bite my lip to silence
the sigh there. His fingers wind tighter around
the curl. It almost seems as if he doesn’t
know he’s doing it—this boy made of smiles
and grand gestures doing something so small
it’s escaped him.
Iker’s eyes drift to the band members who
have circled around a bench where someone
has begun to play a guitaren. Though we can’t
see him, the shiny, precise plucks are a dead
giveaway that the musician is Nik. He’s
always been the kind to pick up any instrument
and immediately know exactly how to play it,
ever since we were children. He’s strumming
the song I used to sing on the docks as a
girl to wish my father safe travels on his
fishing trips. Nik said it always got stuck
in his head.
Iker drops the curl.
Clears his throat.
Adjusts his body so that we’re not touching
in so many places.
It’s over. I know it. Perhaps fantasies
are only meant to come true for a moment.
Surely a trick of the gods.
His eyes linger on the band when he eventually
speaks, but his tone has changed. “Evie,
I love visiting Havnestad, but I don’t like
to step on my cousin’s toes.”
Now my voice isn’t right. Why did Nik have
to play that song? I swallow. “But you aren’t,”
I say, hoping he can’t hear the pleading
in my tone. “Besides, I don’t think Nik
would mind seeing more of you, and there is
the Lithasblot festival coming up in a few
days.”
“Ah, yes, when you people go nuts for Urda,
throw bread at anyone without a double chin,
and run in circles until you pass out.”
“You people?” I say and give him a jab.
Iker may be from across the strait, but he’s
just as much an Øldenburg as Nik. Their family
has ruled Denmark and Sweden for four hundred
years. They know better than anyone not to
discount the harvest the goddess has bestowed
on us. “Don’t poke fun at the games. We
take them very seriously.”
“Oh yes, a life-or-death game of carrying
around the heaviest rock.”
“Or running the length of a log. All useful
skills.” I laugh, happy to have lightened
the mood again.
Iker turns to me. “If I stay for this Lithasblot
extravaganza, you must promise you will scramble
across some recently murdered tree for my
entertainment.”
“If that’s what it takes, then I promise,”
I say, dipping in a mock curtsy.
A laugh escapes from my lips, but Iker’s
attention is locked on my face. Almost as
if he can’t help himself, his thumb grazes
my cheekbone again, down my jaw and to my
mouth. The touch of his finger to my lips
sends color rising in my cheeks as I meet
the glacier blue of his eyes.
“Iker, I—”
“Gooooooood people of Havnestad!” Our
heads whip around as Nik’s voice booms across
the length of the ship. He is still holding
the guitaren, but now he has a crown fashioned
of lemon wedges squashed on his wavy flop
of hair. There’s a huge smile tugging at
his cheeks, and his long arms are thrust high
into the air. He’s actually doing quite
the unintentional impression of Iker, though
only after a few mugs of King Asger’s special
brew. “As your crown prince, I hereby issue
a royal decree that we sing for me on this,
the sixteenth year of my life.”
“Hear, HEAR,” yells Iker, followed by
the rest of the crowd, which has suddenly
crept back into the corners of my vision.
“Excellent. Ruyven has sent the signal for
fireworks. But first, a so—” Nik’s voice
cuts out as Malvina’s strong hand jerks
him down so her lips can meet his ear. The
other hand is gesturing behind them, toward
the cake. Nik stands back up slowly and resets
the guitaren. “The lovely lady Malvina has
informed me we are at a loss for candles.”
Nik points the instrument’s neck at me,
feigned formality still thick in his throat.
“Evelyn?” He raises a brow.
I raise one back.
“Come on, I know you know where they are.”
And I do. Exactly where Nik left them when
he “borrowed” the king’s boat for the
first warm day after a long, ice-filled winter.
“Yes, I do, good prince.”
As much as I don’t want to leave Iker’s
side, I step away, the warmth of him clinging
to my skin for a ghost of a second as we separate.
I snag a lantern that’s dipped low on the
line ringing the deck and move away from the
crowd.
Boots clomping on the stairs, I disappear
belowdecks to the captain’s quarters. The
space is much larger than something that should
be a captain’s anything—the whole place
is nearly bigger than the home I share with
Father and Tante Hansa. The miniature lantern
struggles to keep up with the vastness, illuminating
a halo barely beyond the hem of my party dress.
It’s utterly annoying.
Glancing up the stairs, I confirm that I am
alone; no one followed me below. My back to
the door, I reach a hand into the lantern.
Softly muttered words of old fall from my
lips as my fingers pinch the tip of the candle.
“Brenna bjartr aldrnari. Brenna bjartr aldrari.
Pakka Glöð.”
The candle begins to glow with the full force
of one three times its size.
It’s a small act—something so subtle I
probably could’ve done it in full view of
everyone above. But even something as run-of-the-mill
as a strengthening spell is dangerous here.
Women burned for far less under the Øldenburgs
of yesteryear.
My relatives burned for far less.
Which means there are things about me Nik
and Iker can never know.
Besides, I already took a risk tonight when
I silently urged Malvina’s cake to shed
its sugary skin. I hadn’t tried something
like that since I was a child, but it worked
well enough. Strengthening the candle in the
open would have been pushing my luck, though,
and I’ve never had much of that to begin
with.
Now the cushion of light is more than enough.
I ease my way through the vast space and toward
the pair of chairs under one of the starboard
portholes, a chessboard painted into the oak
table between them.
I’d watched Nik stuff the ship’s allotment
of extra candles into the table’s drawer
while helping him clean up evidence of his
warm-weather get-together. Not that his father
wouldn’t know about our little celebration—dishonesty
has never sat well in Nik’s royal mind—he
just hadn’t wanted to leave the castle’s
harbor crew with more work.
With rescued candles and matches in hand,
I grab the lantern and spin toward the door.
But suddenly in my peripheral vision, I catch
two flashes of shocking white and blue. I
spin back around to where a small halo of
light beacons through the porthole.
My heart sputters to a dead halt as I realize
I don’t know of any fish with markings like
those.
Like human eyes.
Lungs aching for me to remember how to breathe,
I raise the lantern to the porthole, my mind
churning to account for everyone onboard the
ship. Yes, everyone had been there when I
descended the stairs.
Yet, when the halo of light reaches the thick
glass, a friend’s eyes are there, deep blue
and framed by luminous skin, water-darkened
blond waves, and a look of surprise on parted
lips.
“Anna?”
But in the instant I say her name into the
damp cabin, the face vanishes, and I’m left
staring into the indigo deep.
My lungs release and draw in a huge gulp of
air as I race to the next porthole, my breath
coming in rapid spurts as I repeat her name.
But there’s no sign of her beautiful face
at that porthole or the next two.
I stand in the middle of the king’s great
cabin, heart pounding, breath burning in my
lungs, as a heavy sob escapes my lips. Tears
sting my eyes as I realize that even with
Nik’s brotherly friendship and Iker’s
new affection, I’m still just a lonely fisherman’s
daughter.
A lonely fisherman’s daughter wishing that
I could have my sweet friend back. Wishing
hard enough that I’m seeing ghosts.
Wishing so very hard that I’m losing my
mind.
I WIPE MY EYES WITH MY WRIST, THE CANDLES
AND matches still clutched in my fingers.
A couple of deep breaths, and I will myself
through the door and up the stairs, my legs
leaden.
“The good lady has returned with the candles!”
Nik shouts when he sees me, his voice half-singing
in tune with the guitaren.
“And the matches, my prince,” I hear myself
say in a much steadier voice than I’d have
thought possible.
“My dear Evie, always rescuing her prince
from his own lack of forethought.”
“Someone has to, Cousin,” laughs Iker,
rising to his feet while Malvina snatches
the goods from my arms. Immediately, she bustles
behind Nik, spearing the beautiful layers
of fondant with the fat ends of the tapers.
No thank-you from her, even though for anyone
else, her trained manners would require it.
Nik begins the song before they’re all lit.
His voice soars above us all, even over Iker’s
baritone. As usual, I just mouth along to
the words—my singing voice was ruined the
day I lost Anna. Tante Hansa says I’m lucky
that is all the sea took. Nik has his eyes
shut and isn’t even facing his cake, the
flames flickering and twisting behind him,
manipulated by a strong wind from deep within
the Øresund Strait.
My gaze follows the wind into the dark distance.
Just past the edge of our wake, the indigo
skies go pitch-black, the furrowed edges of
an angry line of clouds moving in at a furious
pace.
“Iker,” I breathe.
“. . . Hun skal leve højt hurra . . .” Nik
hits the final line of the traditional birthday
song and turns to blow out the candles, opening
his eyes just as the first of the fireworks
shoots off from the beach. Bursts of white
and red stream across the sky in quick succession,
illuminating Havnestad below and the ring
of mountains surrounding the city proper.
“Iker,” I repeat, my eyes still upon the
clouds closing in. He turns, hand still set
heavily about my waist, and I point to the
storm line as a tendril of lightning strikes
the water just beyond the confines of the
harbor.
A flash of recognition hits his eyes as they
read the distance between the rain and the
ship. “Storm!” he yells, a clap of thunder
cutting off the end of the word. “Everyone
belowdecks! Now!”
But, of course, our party turns toward the
storm rather than away, human curiosity flying
in the face of safety. Iker, Nik, and I rush
into motion as the first fat drops of rain
splatter onto the deck.
Nik begins directing the crowd belowdecks.
Iker is up at the wheel, working to right
the ship toward the harbor after sending its
previous driver—the coal man—down below
to feed the steam engine.
With the rain already sheeting, the boat tips
as I climb the stairs to the stern. I cling
to the rail. There is no magic I can do in
the open to stop this, which makes me grateful
to be the salt of the sea and the daughter
of a fisherman. I’m not helpless in the
least.
Thunder rumbles deep and rich directly overhead.
The cake’s candles and the lanterns ringing
the ship have been blown out by the blustery
wind, and I’m thankful when a flash of lightning
cracks across the sky just long enough to
show me the scene.
Iker—getting the boat going in the right
direction, his feet planted and muscles straining.
Nik—trudging up the stairs after barring
the door down below, his crown of lemons fed
to the sea by the flying wind.
The cake—tipped over and beached on its
massive side as the boat lurches starboard.
Another clap of thunder sounds as I reach
Iker and help him hold the wheel. Iker is
strong enough to steer it by himself, but
the boat’s line noticeably straightens when
I help him maintain control.
“A birthday pleasure cruise!” Iker yells
across the booming skies as I smile at him
through clenched teeth. His eyes dance even
as every tendon in his neck strains to keep
our course. “All clear skies and fancy drinks.
Isn’t that what Nik promised?”
Muscles already screaming, we both focus on
the lighthouse at the edge of the harbor,
still minutes away. A heavy wave crashes along
the deck, taking the remainder of the cake
with it. Nik manages to hold tight to the
stair railing, his white dress shirt plastered
against his skin.
“We’re too slow,” Iker yells into my
ear between peals of thunder.
I nod and grit my teeth further as a gust
of wind pulls the ship portside, yanking the
wheel with it. “I’ve got it,” I say.
“But we won’t go any faster unless—”
I nod toward his prized craft, a present from
his father.
Iker nods, heeding my suggestion. “Nik!”
he yells over the whipping wind and angry
waves. “My schooner! Help me cut it loose!”
Somehow Nik hears him and immediately pulls
himself portside, where Iker’s little boat
is adding too much weight.
Another wave tips up the ship, sending us
starboard. Boots sliding, I manage to keep
us steady, pinning the wheel in place with
all my weight. On the main deck, Nik has made
his way over to the portside rail. He hooks
one long arm around the rail to steady himself,
and then works furiously with his free hand
on my knot. Iker is on his way there.
The boat lurches again, and I close my eyes,
willing land to get closer. When my eyes open,
we might be closer to Havnestad’s docks,
but only by a few feet. I twist my head to
the side and see that Nik nearly has the knot
free.
A whitecap splashes over the side, drenching
Nik. He shakes his head, wavy hair splaying
out to the side. He rights himself, the slick
railing and new floorboards doing him no favors
in traction or leverage. With one final pull,
the rope is completely loose, and slides over
the side of the ship. Nik, much stronger than
he looks, hangs on as the steamer’s equilibrium
changes with the loss of Iker’s schooner.
“Three hundred yards to the royal dock!”
Iker yells, making his way to the wheel. I
look from Nik back to land. The lighthouse
is indeed finally closing in, the blaze atop
the tower looming just below the steely thatch
of clouds.
But not as fast as the biggest wave we’ve
seen yet.
Black as the sky above, the wall of water
splashes hard on the portside, sending Nik
to his knees. I call out for him to stay down—a
lower center of gravity is safer—but my
small voice is swallowed up in the storm.
He stands.
A charge of lightning rips across the sky.
The ship tips, pulled down with the weight
of the wave, rocking Nik headfirst into the
deep.
“NIK!”
I scream his name as loudly as I can. The
boat rights itself, but there’s no sign
of him along the portside. Only wet wood and
sea foam where he once was.
“NIK!” I wail again and let go of the
wheel, passing Iker and sprinting toward the
stairs to the main deck.
My mind moves faster than my wind-battered
body, a string of thoughts running together
in the murk as I dash forward, not caring
or paying attention to the wind, the rain,
the course, or even Iker.
No.
You CANNOT have him, you wicked sea.
Your mermaids will have to take someone else.
Nik belongs to me.
“Evie!” Iker yells. “Don’t! Come back!
It’s not—”
“NIK!” I lunge down the stairs. The deck
boards are slick under my boots, but I race
to the spot where Nik fell. The wind whips
my curls about my face as I squint through
the rain and night at the churning sea below.
“NIK!”
I yell his name over and over, my voice becoming
raw and weak, to the point where it’s barely
a whisper. Finally, we reach the royal dock.
I drop onto the wood before Iker and the coal
man even have time to anchor. I scan the horizon
for any sign of a long arm, a flop of hair,
or a piece of boot.
Iker heaves himself over the railing and onto
the dock next to me, leaving the coal man
to free the rest of the passengers from the
captain’s quarters. “Evie,” he says,
his voice much calmer than it should be—the
sea captain in him overruling his bloodline.
“Look there.” He points to just this side
of the horizon, where the stars have returned,
unhidden by the clouds. “The storm’s almost
over. Nik’s a strong swimmer.”
I nod, my hopes pinned on the reason in his
eyes. “But we still need to find him,”
I say. Everything my father taught me about
the sea kicks in, and I point to a spot in
the churning waves. “We were about there.”
I move my outstretched fingers in a sloping
line in the direction of the wind, following
the line until it lands on the cove side of
Havnestad Beach. “Which means he will most
likely be . . . there.”
I don’t look to Iker for confirmation—I
just take off down the dock, tear onto the
sand, and race across the shoreline in that
direction.
“Nik!” I choke, my voice still raspy and
hopeless against the wind. Iker is on my heels
for a few strides and then ahead of me in
a few more.
Havnestad Cove is part jutting rock, part
silty beach. There’s a rolling W shape to
it, and a few large boulders form footstep
islands toward its center, before the waters
become too deep. In good weather, it’s a
beautiful escape from the rest of the harbor.
In bad weather, it’s a hurricane in a birdbath.
Iker points to the biggest island—Picnic
Rock. “I’m going there to see what I can.”
The wind is already calming, the rain tapering
off. Even the lightning seems to be behind
us, disappearing with the storm into the mountains.
The swiftness of such a powerful storm confounds
me. The magic in my blood prickles at the
strangeness, but I have no time to think of
things beyond this world.
I tilt my chin toward a mass of rocks farther
along the shore, the point that makes the
W by jutting deep into the middle of the cove.
It’s just tall enough that it blinds us
from the remainder of the beach.
“I’ll climb up there and take a look on
the other side.”
“Wait!” Iker says, his face weary. For
once, he doesn’t seem to know what to say.
He reaches his hand through my hair and pulls
me close. My heart is pounding.
“Iker, we ca—” The words are whispers
on my tongue—that we can’t delay, that
he shouldn’t slow me down—when he tips
my chin up and his lips are on mine.
I breathe him in, long and deep, and for a
moment we’re not on a gritty beach, soaked
to the bone, searching for Nik. We’re somewhere
far from here. A place where class, title—none
of that matters. Somewhere that surely doesn’t
exist outside of this instant. Another trick
of the gods.
He pulls back, and I’m stunned still, staring
into his cool eyes.
“Be careful,” he says.
Shaken back to reality, I pick up my waterlogged
skirts and run along the coastline to the
wall of stone. The swift clouds have almost
reached their end, their tail nearly directly
above the cove entrance. Starry night reigns
above the massive sea beyond, calm waters
with it. My eyes are constantly scanning the
waves, looking for any sign of Nik.
But there’s nothing.
I steal a glance back at Iker. He’s already
made it to Picnic Rock, hoisting himself up.
I breathe a sigh of relief that the stormy
churn didn’t wash him away and turn back
to the approaching boulder just steps ahead.
I’ve climbed this giant rock hundreds of
times since childhood, as have most of Havnestad’s
youth. I know the placement of the fingerholds
with my eyes shut; my boots automatically
drift to the perfect places to wedge themselves
before taking another step up. The rain has
all but stopped now, and the crag of stone
is mostly damp, not slick.
I lug myself on top and scan the waters again,
squinting at every irregularity, struggling
to use the limited moonlight to make out what
is yet another coastal rock and what might
be Nik. I close my eyes, dread piling at my
feet as I pivot toward the hidden portion
of the cove. When my eyes spring open, I have
to blink again to make sure my mind isn’t
playing tricks. A flash of bright-white fabric
swims on the distant sandy line.
My heart swells with hope. I scramble down
the rock and onto the other side of the beach.
My feet work overtime to propel my body forward
as the wet sand swallows my boots with each
step.
Lightning radiates over the mountains, illuminating
the sky for a flash—long enough for my brain
to register the outline of Nik’s body against
the sand.
And the form of a girl hovering over him.
“NIK!” I yell, my voice coming back to
me.
In response comes Iker’s baritone from behind,
“Evie!”
But I don’t wait for him. I don’t even
turn in Iker’s direction, keeping my eyes
only on Nik and the girl leaning over him,
her body still mostly submerged. Without another
stroke of lightning, I can’t make out much
more than her long, long hair—so long it
drapes over the white of Nik’s shirt.
The girl’s head tilts up in the moonlight
as if she’s just now noticed me running
toward her at full speed. The lightning returns
in a burst, and though my legs keep moving,
my heart skids to a stop.
Large blue eyes. Butter-blond curls. Creamy
flush of skin.
It’s the girl. The one from the porthole.
Anna?
No, it can’t be.
Recognition seems to fill the girl’s eyes,
and her features skip from contented calm
to a pure rush of panic. Panic that sends
her straight into motion. A gust of wind pushes
her hair over the curve of her shoulder as
she takes one hasty and last glance at Nik’s
face before heaving herself fully into the
water.
“Wait!” I yell as best I can, but it’s
useless with her ears deep under the waves.
In less than a breath, I get to Nik and crash
to the sand next to him, pulling his chest
to mine, my ear to his mouth. A rush of air
from his lips touches my cheek as Iker yells
both our names from behind.
Nik’s lungs work in great rasps, but they
work. His eyes are closed, but he seems to
be conscious.
“Evie . . .”
“I’m here, Nik. I’m here.”
A ghost of a smile touches his lips. “Evie
. . . keep singing, Evie.”
Confused, I begin correcting him. “Nik,
I’m not—I don’t . . .”
My mouth goes dry. I scan the waters for any
sign of the girl. The girl who looks like
Anna all grown up. The girl who must like
to sing the way my friend did as a child.
At first, there’s still nothing. Just ever-calming
waves and starry night, backlit by the summer
solstice moon.
But then, just at the edge of the cove, I
see it.
Blond hair gone silver under the clear moon,
peeking up for a swift moment before the girl
dives back underwater. A trail of sea spray
flies up in her wake—and with it comes something
more.
The perfect outline of a tail fin.
FOUR YEARS BEFORE
The sun was out, as fierce and as hot as possible
in Havnestad. It wasn’t as fierce or hot
as it is in other places, but memorable to
those in the mild-mannered Øresund Kingdoms,
much more accustomed to Mother Nature’s
cold shoulder than her steamy smile, though
it was the height of summer.
Two girls, one with waves of blond, one with
curls of black, pranced along the shoreline.
Their voices lifted toward the naked June
sun, carried aloft by a deep wind from within
the strait.
A boy, already as tall as a man, trailed them,
piccolo to his lips, writing a tune for the
girls’ merry lyrics.
Despite the sun, the main beach was clear,
the majority of Havnestad hauling fish and
hunting whales at sea, the bustle of a modern
economy weathering a boom. They would flood
the shores with catch and tales soon enough,
returning that night for the days-long Lithasblot
festival and the midsummer full moon. For
now, the whole stretch of sand belonged to
the two girls and their boy.
The waves, heavy and exuberant, churned in
the strong wind, tossing themselves at the
girls’ ankles—bare without anyone there
to correct them. The boy’s boots were on—his
feet were gangly and hairy in a way they hadn’t
been last summer, and he didn’t want the
girls to see. He stayed on dry sand, just
beyond the waves’ reach, coal-dark eyes
pinned on the girls’ delicate toes, which
also seemed to have changed in a year, but
only maybe in the way he couldn’t look away
from the flash of skin beneath their skirts.
They went on like that until the girls suddenly
stopped—singing, prancing, everything—so
suddenly that the boy bumped into the raven-curled
girl’s back. She laughed it off, but both
girls’ eyes were locked on the sea. Watching
the whitecaps with wonder, adventure flashing
in their eyes.
The one with the blond waves and ocean-blue
eyes spoke first. “She’s angry—foaming
at the mouth.”
“Are you calling the sea a rabid dog?”
asked the raven-haired one. “She wouldn’t
like that much.”
“I suppose not.”
A black brow pitched above eyes blue like
midnight. “Touch the sandbar and return
to shore?” She smiled, lips pinned in a
slight twist. “Dare you.”
The blond girl considered it, chewing on her
lip, reading the waves. Finally, in answer,
she began unlacing her dress’s bodice.
The boy sat on the sand behind the girls,
playing the piccolo so they’d think he was
distracted, not paying an inch of attention
to them as they stripped to their petticoats.
Even in surreptitious glances, their shoulders
and arms were things of beauty, smooth as
the marble statues his mother had commissioned
for the tulip garden. So beautiful they made
his cheeks hot. He knew he should not look—it
wasn’t right, not at the age they were getting
to be—but still, he watched.
The blond girl watched back, her eyes finding
him, cheeks pinking as her clothes fell to
the sand. The raven-curled girl thwacked her
on the shoulder, dark eyes big and knowing.
No secrets between friends, except those in
plain sight.
When the girls were ready, they stood, dresses
neatly folded, and pointed slim fingers toward
the sea.
On the count of three, they were gone.
I DON’T BELIEVE IN MERMAIDS. I DON’T.
THEY ARE JUST an abomination ancients like
Tante Hansa dream up to keep children from
doing especially dim-witted things. If you
touch that hot pot . . . if you eat that whole
cake . . . if you take that candy . . . the
mermaids will steal you away. We’re superstitious,
children of the sea, but we’re not gullible.
Mermaids don’t exist.
But I know what I saw. I know who I saw.
Nik, for his part, doesn’t seem to remember
much. He thinks I rescued him. He thinks I
sang to him.
It’s been more than a day, and I still haven’t
told him that he’s lost his mind if he thinks
that’s what happened. Mostly because I don’t
have an answer to what really did. None of
it makes any sense.
No, I don’t believe in mermaids.
But I do have a strong belief in friendship—more
than anything in this world.
I believed it with Anna.
And I believe it with Nik.
Iker—I don’t know what to think of Iker,
though he’s standing right before me on
the royal dock, borrowed crew packing a borrowed
ship behind him.
“Come—the sea calls.” Iker brushes away
a few of my curls and cups his hand about
my ear as if to amplify the sea’s ancient
voice. He leans down, his cheek brushing right
against mine, his lips warm next to my skin
as he whispers, “Evelynnnnn.”
His enthusiasm makes my heart skip, and I
wish I could go, but Father is leaving this
morning as well, and he hates the idea of
me being aboard a different ship while he
is at sea too. He’s superstitious to a fault,
even if it’s just for a quick trip up the
Jutland and back before Sankt Hans Aften and
the opening of the Lithasblot festival. Iker
is enchanted by sightings of a large whale—one
that would feed Rigeby Bay for weeks in both
meals and trade. I hate it, but I know Iker
must go—the seafaring season waits for no
one, not even a prince.
“I’m so very sorry to disappoint,” I
say. And I am. This time with him has been
strangely magical, even if all we’ve done
is sit with Nik, telling stories to make him
smile as he recovers.
“Too late, the sea is already disappointed—your
skills during the storm were top-notch. You’re
a sailor she needs upon her waves.” His
eyes flash, the curve of his mouth serious.
Vulnerable, even, as strange as that is. But
I don’t—I can’t—let myself think that
it’s he who needs me and not the sea. Reality
doesn’t work that way.
“The sea will have to wait.”
“And so will I.” He bends down to kiss
me then, and though it’s the second time,
it’s still a shock—a deep dive into ice-capped
waters.
“You don’t have to go,” I say when we
part, my voice small and slurred.
“What’s that?” he says, pretending not
to have heard. “You don’t have to stay?”
He grabs my hand in both of his and begins
to tug me toward the ship, full of crew waiting
for his instruction. “Splendid, let’s
get going—you steer; I’ll sip portvin
and keep an eye out for the whale.”
I laugh and let him tug me a little farther
up the gangplank than I should. In my heart,
I don’t believe in Father’s superstitions.
And yet I have superstitions of my own. Nik
is still recovering. I can’t leave. What
if he took a turn for the worse while I was
gone?
No, I must stay.
Iker will come back. He says he will.
I know he will.
Something changed that night on the steamer.
More during the storm than in the huddled
moments before—we’d seen each other in
our element. The salt of the sea, the both
of us. And despite choosing to stay, it is
the very last thing I want Nik to know about.
Most especially the kissing. But it shouldn’t
be too hard to keep a secret from my best
friend—after all, I’ve been keeping my
magic from Nik his whole life.
I step down from the gangplank and onto the
dock. With a wave and a shout to his crew,
Iker is off, taking our secret leagues away
as I tuck it deep within me. I watch as he
leaves the harbor, standing there just long
enough to glimpse him turning back, my hand
ready to wave. And then I set out for one
more good-bye and my daily duties, Tante Hansa’s
amethyst heavy in my pocket.
No, I don’t believe in mermaids. But I am
willing to believe in whatever it is that
happens when I kiss the amethyst to the bow
of my father’s ship before an expedition.
What happens when I cast the spell I created
using centuries-old magical wisdom.
It’s only been a few weeks, but already
it has worked, bringing in far more catch
than by this time last year. I smile when
I see the fishermen celebrating on the docks
now. After four years of suffering through
the Tørhed, a barrenness so severe the town’s
fishing fleet decreased by half, these hearty
cheers are welcome sounds. I haven’t heard
them since before Anna’s death; the grumbles
from tired fishermen coming ashore to restock
on salted meat and limes have filled our ears
instead.
After three years of the Tørhed, King Asger
knew that praying to the gods was no longer
enough. Havnestad had to find a new way to
stay afloat. The royal steamship was ordered,
and any man not at sea was put to work building
the boat from late summer to first frost,
shaping wood, and fitting sheets of metal
to the smokestack.
But even that ship, hammered together by the
strength of this fine town, was not enough
to keep all of Havnestad’s bellies fed.
The steamer was a one-time measure. Even the
crown can’t afford a new ship every year.
I had to do something.
So, as I’ve done since the summer of Anna’s
death, I stole into Tante Hansa’s room while
she was off playing her weekly turn of whist
down at Fru Agnata’s shack. Hansa’s bedroom
is a stifling place, with the fire lit every
night, even in the summer. Dried roses line
the walls in a ring as high as she can reach—the
hundreds of them a testament to her belief
that their scent and beauty are superior to
the tulips so popular throughout the Øresund
Kingdoms.
Beneath the line of roses, in a corner opposite
the flue, there’s a sea chest draped in
shadow and an ancient moose hide. Inside is
everything the Øldenburgs fear, all they
have banished by law: gemstones, age-stained
books, cobalt bottles sealed with pinches
of cork and wax. The very same items Tante
Hansa used on me when I resurfaced in Nik’s
arms four years ago, Anna nowhere to be found.
When I’d been in bed, nearly dead myself,
watched over by Hansa and spoon-fed elixirs
tasting of perfume and age. And aged they
certainly are, passed down in shadow generations
for centuries. Someday they will belong to
me, I suppose.
That day I took a purple stone—one so small
that I hoped it would escape Hansa’s notice,
but big enough to have an impact. I snagged
one of the tattered books with crumbling spines,
too, fishing it out from where it was packed
under a cake of beeswax and a marble mortar
and pestle.
Hours after lights out, I crept down to the
beach, but well beyond Havnestad Cove. As
the shoreline thins, becoming one with the
rocky mountain, sharp boulders jut out from
the sea. The water is deeper there and the
waves choppy, but in between the shadow of
two large rocks is a swath of sand. Overhead,
stone from the edge of Havnestad has formed
into a perfect arch, the result of Urda coaxing
the sea into this crevice for thousands of
years.
This place doesn’t have a name, as far as
I know. I’ve never seen anyone come here,
and it’s hidden from view on the beach and
by the boulders from the sea. I’ve taken
to calling it Greta’s Lagoon, after my mother.
She would have liked a place like this. Deep
in the shadows of the lagoon is a small cave
barely large enough to fit two, but it’s
plenty big to store the few tinctures and
inks Tante Hansa has entrusted to me.
I moved away the few small boulders I use
to hide the entrance and lit a candle. With
the amethyst stone cradled in one hand, I
slid the book under the meager light. The
words were ancient and yet familiar, recalling
our great goddess, Urda, and the power she
bestows on the land and sea. As the waves
splashed against the rocks outside, I read
the scrawl over and over, swirling the spells
across my tongue. It took until nearly daylight,
but finally I could feel the magic tingle
in my blood.
After nearly three months of practice, I spelled
Father’s boat for the first time.
Three days after that, he came home with his
first whale in more than two years. It was
thin, but fat enough for all the joy that
came with it.
Now the spell is a must.
The need to keep Father safe and prosperous
is thick in my veins each morning when I wake,
jamming my heart with anxiety until I can
do my job. My part.
Even when I’ve done my duty and he’s away
for days, I come to the harbor and spell any
ship docked and still. The fishermen are used
to seeing me daily now. They don’t seem
to find it strange that I’m always there,
letting my closed palm trail along the salt-worn
bodies of ships, old and trusty.
And today is the day I begin to do more. Along
with what I cannot claim, I have been working
away on something I can. Something all of
Havnestad will recognize as helpful and not
some fate of Urda.
“Evie, my girl!” Father is hauling a crate
up to the deck of his whaler—Little Greta,
also named for my mother. There isn’t a
single crate of supplies left on the dock
beside the ship. I’ve only just caught him.
“I wasn’t sure you’d come.”
I laugh lightly, fingers tight over the gem
in my palm. “Just because I want you to
stay doesn’t mean I’ll miss you going.”
Father’s mouth settles into a tart line,
the sun spots marring his forehead crinkling
up to his black hair—he’s Italian by birth,
though he’s Danish through and through.
We walk up the gangplank together. He drops
the crate two feet from the innovation I know
will make these desolate seas that much easier
to fish—a permanent cure my magic cannot
provide. Mounted proudly to the mainmast,
half-harpoon, half-rifle, my darting gun looks
as shiny and perfect as I’d hoped.
Father hugs me close. “My Evelyn, the inventor.”
“It was nothing,” I say, though we both
know that’s not true. It took me the whole
winter to create one from an old rifle and
modified harpoon, but if my calculations are
correct, the contraption will send out both
a bomb lance and a tether harpoon, narrowing
the chances of a whale escaping. If all goes
well with Father’s maiden voyage, we might
be able to transform the way Havnestad snags
its whales.
“It’s not nothing. It’ll be a revolution.”
I tilt my face up to his, brow raised. “It’ll
still be a revolution if you wait a week.”
Father bristles at the sore spot between us.
He’s not the only fisherman headed out during
the festival, though far more are staying
than leaving, bolstered by their recent luck—my
recent help. But he’s the only one I care
about. And, as the royal fisherman, he’s
the only one King Asger cares about as well.
“There will be other Lithasblot festivals,
Evelyn. If you’ve been pelted with bread
once, you’ve been pelted with bread a thousandfold.”
“But—”
He cuts me off with rough fingers on the point
of my chin.
“But nothing. I have to seize my luck while
it’s there.” Father’s grizzled old thumb
settles on my bottom lip. “I’ll return
for the close of the festival—the ball.”
Despite my disappointment at yet another good-bye,
I form a tight smile after his words. “If
you’ve seen me once in my only nice dress,
you’ve seen me a thousandfold.”
He leans in and gives me a quick kiss on the
cheek, his beard both soft and rough against
my skin.
“Take care of Hansa, my dear.”
I hug him to my chest, the cloying scent of
pipe tobacco catching in my lungs.
“If only she’d allow such a thing, I would.”
He releases me with a single squeeze of my
forearm. I turn for the gangplank, one last
look at both him and my first stab at whaling
innovation. When I’m back on the sun-ruined
wood of the dock, Father yells for his men
to hoist up the gangplank and anchor.
Before he’s gone, and with the sailors distracted
by departure duties, I take my chance and
press my little stone to the ship, right under
my mother’s name, painted in block letters
across the stern. My eyes flutter to a close,
and I whisper my spell into the breeze coming
in off the Øresund Strait.
IT’S A PERFECT NIGHT FOR BURNING WITCHES.
That’s what Sankt Hans Aften is, after all.
A celebration in the name of ridding people
like me from this earth through flames, drowning,
banishment—whatever seemed right at the
time.
Today, thankfully, witches are only burned
in effigy. It’s the traditional opening
of Havnestad’s version of Lithasblot. Ours
is the earliest in the Øresund Strait, but
we’re also the longest festival, five whole
days, drawing people from all around to watch
the games, sing songs in celebration of Urda,
and taste plates of tvøst og spik: black
whale meat, pink blubber, and sunny potatoes.
Even through the Tørhed, the people of Havnestad
have always been willing to sacrifice their
limited food supply to honor the goddess.
As the bonfire grows hot, shooting tendrils
of flames high into the salmon-toned sky,
the festival is ready to begin. First is King
Asger’s speech of love and gamesmanship.
Now Nik’s speech of love and gamesmanship.
For on the night of that treacherous storm,
Nik, thankfully, still came of age. And as
tradition demands, he must take the reins
of the festival—near-drowning is not an
excuse.
Thus, since regaining most of his strength,
he’s been shut away, pacing the halls of
the palace with his father’s words on his
lips. I’ve heard him run through it twice—before
his birthday and after, and both times he
was excellent, if not a hair too fast. Still,
that’s just because this is new to him.
I know he’ll be amazing.
But Crown Prince Asger Niklas Bryniulf Øldenburg
III, first in line to the throne of the sovereign
kingdom of Havnestad, does not share my assessment.
Nik is nearly white with nerves. His long
fingers shake as he tugs his hair flat. This
day is already hard for the both of us—the
fourth anniversary of Anna’s drowning—and
with the pressure of the speech added atop
that, Nik looks as if he might keel over.
I don’t hesitate to snag a hand and press
my fingers around his. Somehow, seeing him
so nervous calms my own reservations—about
my innovation’s trial run with Father, about
the fact Iker has yet to arrive. I squeeze
Nik’s fingers. “You’ve done nothing
but practice for the past week. You’ll be
just fine.”
“But I’m not cut out for this, Evie.”
“Of course you are! You’re cut from the
Øldenburg cloth. Kings for a thousand years.”
I lean in, my face consuming his vision. “This
speech is in your blood.”
Nik turns red and averts his gaze. “I think
that particular blood spilled out of me when
I bashed my leg on that rock at ten.”
I nearly laugh, thinking of Nik passing out
at the sight of his own blood. Right in the
middle of a trail leading up Lille Bjerg Pass.
Anna and I stripped off our stockings and
tied them tightly above the gash across his
shin before bracing him between us and hobbling
down the mountain.
“Think of your birthday. You didn’t seem
at all nervous while you sang on a bench with
lemons in your hair.”
“That wasn’t the whole kingdom. This is.”
“So? What’s a few more faces?”
He lets out a very royal snort. “Since when
does a ‘few’ mean a hundred times more?
And maybe my disastrous birthday is not the
best image to calm my nerves.”
“Oh, don’t be dramatic.”
Nik cocks a brow. “Oh, but you’re not
plenty dramatic when you make moon eyes at
the harbor, scouting for a certain sailor
from Rigeby Bay?”
I say nothing, my wit tied to a stone in the
pit of my stomach. Despite myself, I squint
out at the water, my heart willing Iker’s
boat to appear. But the sea beyond the harbor
is clear, all the visiting ships and off-duty
whalers already in port.
Nik sighs, and I know he’s beating himself
up for such a quip—and again I’m thankful
he knows nothing of the kisses Iker and I
shared. He squeezes me close again, the nervous
tremble subdued. “He’ll be here. Iker
makes his own rules, but he never breaks his
word.”
That was the last thing he said to me before
Queen Charlotte pulled him away for his final
speech preparations. I sink to the sand and
sit, a little doll in my lap dressed in black
and white. Ready for the ashes. I can barely
force myself to play along. And without Nik
by my side, this year I play along alone.
I suppose I could join the castle workers—I’ve
known them since I was a small child. But
I’m not truly one of them. And the other
girls my age? Well, they’re never really
an option—they’ve made that much clear
over the years.
Maybe banishment wouldn’t be such a bad
thing—I could just break out my magic as
we burn our little witch dolls and leave this
place for good. But then I’d leave Nik for
good too. And implicate my entire family.
So, I sit alone—the secret witch, the prince’s
friend who doesn’t know her place.
I am well within eyeshot of Nik as he readies
to speak—in the event that his courage has
retreated up Lille Bjerg Pass—but far enough
to the side that I have a clear view of the
sea in my periphery.
He will come.
He said he would.
You shouldn’t care anyway.
I turn my attention back to the royal family.
And to the flames I must face before Nik’s
big moment.
There’s a traditional speech honoring this
“celebration” too. And though the king
may have ceded his duties to Nik, Queen Charlotte
would never give up her chance to speak out
against the horrors of witchcraft.
The queen is a beauty by any measure, all
fine bone structure and swanlike grace. Her
hair is curled and coiled atop her head, a
deep blond halo around a crown of sapphires
and diamonds. When she steps forward in the
sand, she looks every bit a painting in the
firelight.
In her hands is her ceremonial first doll—clothed
in blood red.
As if the death of every Dane in the past
six hundred years was the fault of a witch.
As if the Øldenburgs hadn’t burned hundreds
of women with flimsy proof.
As if “the witch hunter king,” King Christian
IV, hadn’t been proud of the name he earned
and of the lives he ruined.
“Good evening, dear ones.” Queen Charlotte
smiles to the crowd, and it’s like ice cracking
under pressure. “On this night, we not only
celebrate the beginning of Havnestad’s Lithasblot,
but we remember the hardships endured by our
ancestors.”
In the shadows, my knuckles turn white as
I clench the doll in my lap. This part is
almost worse than tossing a replica of myself
into the fire.
“We live in safety and harmony in the Øresund
Kingdoms because of the courage of King Christian
IV. We live in safety and harmony because
of the laws he put in place. Witchcraft has
no place except in the depths of hell.”
The queen hoists the red doll above her head
so hard its little witch’s hat falls, the
fire sucking it into the flames. “Shall
there be any devils on our shores, know you
do not belong here nor in this world.” I
swear her eyes find me in this moment. “The
light will win, and you shall be swallowed
deep into the flames and returned to your
horned maker.”
The crowd erupts, and Queen Charlotte spins
on the spot, tossing the witch into the bonfire—royally
ousting us because our power is a threat to
her own.
We are to form an orderly line circling the
fire, but I can’t do that. I won’t do
that. Instead, I stand and toss my doll over
the heads of those charging forward, eager
to murder little wooden models of me. My mother.
My aunt. My father’s family.
I look for Nik then, who follows suit with
a smile on his face. Somewhere Tante Hansa
is laughing, her distinctive cackle hitting
my ear. I know it’s a ruse to protect us,
but I don’t know how she can pretend to
enjoy it so much. She even goes so far as
to have the most colorful doll, meddling with
pastes and dyes until she can ensure its little
outfit will be the brightest on the beach.
This year, hers is a stunning orange, thanks
to a customer who unknowingly added to her
fun by paying her in turmeric.
It’s ironic: the same townspeople who come
to her when they burn their skin, grateful
for her ancient medicinal treatments, turn
little wooden replicas of our ancestors to
ash each year on this date. And she just laughs
in their faces like it’s nothing. As hundreds
rush the fire, I sink back down to the sand
and wipe my hands on my skirts. It’s just
sweat, but it almost feels like blood.
When every last witch has been tossed, the
crowd retreats. Nik has stepped a measure
in front of his parents to the most prominent
spot on the sand, the bonfire at his back.
Even in the ochre light, his skin is unnaturally
pale. I make my gaze as heavy and focused
as possible, not even so much as blinking
until he catches my eye. I give him a smile
and a nod.
You’ll be splendid.
His lips curl up, and he clears his throat
with a deep breath.
“Good people of Havnestad, welcome to the
opening night of Lithasblot, when we honor
Urda and give thanks for her blessings and
bounty, be it from the sea or from land.”
The fire crackles happily behind him, the
tallest flames licking at the stars. Despite
the crush of people, only that crackle and
the lapping of the sea fills in the practiced
pause in the traditional speech. We all know
it by heart—and could join Nik in its recital,
if it were appropriate. Most days, he’s
one of us. Just Nik. But tonight he’s our
crown prince, and our duty as subjects outweighs
our familiarity.
So we are quiet.
Nik glances up at his pause and meets my eye
again. I nod him forward even though his color
has suddenly returned.
“These next four days are a celebration.
Games, races, songs, and feasts in our goddess’s
name. Let us not forget that it is all for
her. It is fun. It is merry. But it has a
utility—a reason. Urda.”
There is an audible gasp in the crowd—Nik
has gone off script. He’s speaking from
the heart, and I couldn’t be prouder.
“Last year, we did the same as we will do
this week,” Nik goes on, his voice gathering
strength. “We pelted our thinnest with bread.
We sang to Urda. We watched as I carried the
heaviest rock down the beach.”
At this, he flexes a bicep and flashes a smile—all
his nerves replaced with bravado. A few chuckles
carry through the crowd, but there is only
one heavy guffaw—issued by Tante Hansa,
from her corner at the table reserved for
the ancients.
Nik rounds on her with a pronounced grin and
then pulls his brows together. His tone swings
back to serious. “Yes, I am aware my scrawny
feats of strength are quite hysterical. But
those are on display daily”—he grins again—“and
they are not why we do this year after year.
We do this for Urda. And some years she teaches
us a lesson and reminds us of her power.”
Nik pauses, the air heavy and silent. Not
even the bonfire dares to crackle.
“My father stood on this exact spot a year
ago and recited the very same speech he has
said for thirty years. Which his father before
him recited for thirty years before that.
Yet we were in the thick of the Tørhed—the
third year running. And did it improve when
we came together to sing songs about Urda
until our voices were rough and fingers bleeding
on our guitarens? No. Did it improve when
I defeated all you weaklings in the rock carry?
No.”
Only Tante Hansa is brave enough to cackle
this time. But no one turns her way. All eyes
are on our crown prince. Even the king and
queen are hanging on his every word.
“Let us remember that though we celebrate
her, Urda owes us not a morsel. Just like
the tide that laps our shores—her tide,
her shores—she can take as swiftly as she
can give.”
Nik pauses, his coal-dark eyes on the harbor
over our heads. I realize he’s referencing
Anna too. Honoring her as something Urda claimed
for her own, the sea doing the goddess’s
bidding.
“So, let us honor Urda this week, not just
celebrate her name, but truly honor her. She
is our queen—forgive me, Mother. The land
that gives us bounty. The sea that brings
us our supper as much as coins in our pocket.
She is more than a goddess—she is us. Havnestad.
And all the people within it. Without her,
we are nothing. No magic can trick her. No
words can ply her. No will can sway her. She
is queen, and we are simply her subjects.”
He comes to a full stop, eyes on the waves
beyond the crowd, posture firm and tall—regal.
Perhaps stunned by his originality and honesty,
it takes the whole of Havnestad a few moments
to process that he’s finished. I stand and
begin to cheer and clap. Nik’s eyes find
me, and there’s a wink of relief that brushes
across his features before my view of him
is blocked—every last person leaping to
their feet, hoots at their lips and applause
gone wild. And somehow it feels as if he’s
leagues away.
IT’S IMPOSSIBLE TO SEE HIM AFTER THAT.
All the people want to shake his hand. Tell
him how awed they are by his thoughtfulness.
About how poised he was. How kingly he sounded.
How impressed they were and are.
Nik is swallowed by their affections.
And though I wait on the beach for him to
resurface, he doesn’t. Whisked away for
the night in a crowd of his subjects. Every
other creature eventually peters out for the
night too. A rush and then a trickle in exit
until it’s just me, a hot pile of kindling,
and a few poor souls who have lost the battle
of alertness to free hvidtøl and a patch
of soft sand.
I stand, legs stiff in my boots, eyes toward
the harbor, breathing in the sharp, salty
air. My throat tightens and tears threaten
my eyes.
He’s going to be king, Evie.
I want to laugh at my foolishness for thinking
I’d always have him. Of course everything
is going to change.
The moon is so bright that I can see the length
of the beach without any other aid. Too bright
for my dark mood, but maybe a walk will do
me good. Clear my head. I should be happy
for him, after all.
I make my way down the docks first, taking
the worn planks in careful steps as ships
large and small clank and bump at the sea’s
discretion.
Naturally, the royal dock is the largest in
the harbor—with room for the king’s giant
steamer, my father’s craft, and a dozen
other royal ships, boats, schooners, and skiffs.
There’s a pole at the end that is empty,
though—the spot where the king’s steamship
should be.
I stare at the water there for a moment, wishing
for the second time tonight that his boat
would materialize among the gentle rolling
waves. Just suddenly appear with Iker aboard,
a shine in his eyes and laughter on his lips.
That he’d jump off the bow before anchoring,
not able to hold himself back from me a moment
longer. That he’d pull me in deeply into
his arms for another kiss.
I blink and the thought has vanished.
The pole is still untethered.
There is not a single ship on the horizon.
I step off the dock, my back to the waves
that took Anna, my head and heart throbbing
with the wish that she would return, too.
That I’d have my friend back. That I wouldn’t
feel the need to pin my hopes on boys who
I should’ve known all along would only care
about me until they hit that invisible line
in the sand—blood—and then let me down.
Though maybe, being highborn, Anna would’ve
felt the same way.
I am too restless to run home to bed. To nod
and smile at Hansa’s drunken tale of her
grand evening with her grand friends—as
if those friends didn’t just burn thousands
of us. So I walk along the water to the cove
side, the moonlight guiding my steps, catching
on the shimmering flecks of sand to create
a brilliant path along the shoreline.
I don’t have a plan, and I don’t need
one. I just need a chance to wear myself out
enough that I fall asleep unencumbered by
the sadness dragging my heart down to my ankles.
I do have friends who aren’t royal. I do.
I have the kids from school who tolerate me
for Nik’s sake, but only really when their
prince is around. But for the most part, all
I see when I greet their faces is the disapproval
reflected in their eyes.
That girl—couldn’t save her mother.
That girl—lived while her best friend drowned.
That girl—thinks her father’s job gives
her keys to the castle.
That girl—thinks herself more than a passing
fancy for the playboy prince.
I meet the first rocks of the cove and stand
there, letting the salt air toss my curls
about my face. The wind here always seems
so cleansing—like it sweeps away grime both
physical and mental with one exhale from the
Øresund Strait.
Tonight the cove is calm. The waves lap gently
about the shore, kissing both the sand and
the rock formations with the same delicate
precision. There is no one else in sight,
and this dress isn’t anything special—nothing
I have is special—so I yank off my boots
and stockings and place them carefully on
a patch of beach not likely to be touched
by the tide. The sand sticking to my toes,
I hop onto the first footstep island and leap
from stone to stone until I make it to Picnic
Rock.
Though it’s damp from the recent high tide,
the slab isn’t so wet it’s uncomfortable.
I gather my skirts, pull my knees to my chest,
and sit there with my eyes closed, letting
the sea’s charge wash over me.
Finally, my heartbeat slows, and I can feel
exhaustion creeping in. But I can’t sleep
here. I force myself to stand on stiff legs
and grab my things. There’s barely a breeze,
but a tingle runs up my spine. I cross my
arms over my chest, but I can’t get rid
of the cold. I squint into the night, at the
shadow where the sea meets the rock formation
splitting the cove, when I swear I see a flash
of white skin.
“Hello?” I call, my body shivering.
Only the wind answers, gently gaining strength
from well past the harbor and deep within
the sea.
I am suddenly awake, and I turn my attention
again to the rock wall. But there’s nothing
to see but shadow and waves.
Maybe it was the octopus who’s made the
cove his home, taunting me the same way he
taunts Tante Hansa, who would like nothing
more than to bottle every last drop of his
ink.
But probably not. My eyes are playing tricks
on me again.
Just as they must have on Nik’s birthday.
“Perhaps you need to avoid the cove when
the moon is strong, Evelyn,” I mutter. The
moon can do funny things to a witch.
I can hear it now, another strain in the chorus
of pity: That girl—seeing apparitions in
the moonlight.
FOUR YEARS BEFORE
The boy heard the splashes, one right after
another, and stood, piccolo forgotten, eyes
only on the sea. He held his breath, waiting
for the first one to surface. They were both
strong swimmers, but the raven-curled girl
made a habit of winning.
It was a hundred yards to the sandbar. A worthy
swim on any day, but as the boy surveyed the
sea again, he knew this was not just any sea.
These were not just any waves.
The sea was angry.
The boy held his breath and took a step toward
the water, careful not to get too close—his
mother had often lectured him on the damage
salt water could do to his fine leather boots.
The blond girl surfaced first. She pulled
in a deep breath and then went back under,
the sandbar in her sights, still seventy-five
yards away.
The boy scanned the water for dark hair. Took
a breath. Squinted right at the spot where
she should’ve surfaced. Still nothing.
The blonde bobbed up again. Now ten yards
closer to the sandbar and not looking back.
No dark hair to be seen.
He took another step forward. A wave took
full advantage and marked his foot. On reflex,
he glanced down. Yes, the leather was completely
soaked. But he didn’t care. Eyes immediately
back on the sea. Heart pounding. The wet boot
already coming off.
There. In the distance, thirty yards out.
Not the crown of a raven-haired head.
A single hand, reaching for air.
The boy dove in, full breath cinched in his
lungs, and opened his eyes. Nothing but the
murky deep and the sting of salt.
Thinking of the girls, of the hand, he surfaced
early. He would keep his stroke above the
waves, his head close to the surface. He was
a strong swimmer, and his new height had not
diminished his natural strength, but the undertow
was fiercer than he’d ever felt, constantly
tugging at his pant legs. A force from the
deep pulling him toward the harem of mermaids
all Havnestad children were told lived at
the bottom of the sea.
At the surface, he saw nothing. Not a strand
of hair, nor a flash of hand. But he knew
where they were. He knew where he must go.
Twenty more yards and he opened his eyes to
the sea again. Looked down. Where the undertow
had pulled him.
Black hair curled up like a cloud of ink,
pale fingers stretched toward him. Her face
hidden. He dove, hoping it wasn’t too late.
Lungs burning for air, he surfaced, one arm
hooked under her shoulders. The force of the
swim had pushed the curls from her face. Her
features bordered on blue, and he couldn’t
tell if she was breathing.
All he knew was that he had her.
“Come on, Evie. Come on.” He prayed to
the old gods as well as the Lutheran one when
he had the breath, his body fighting the tow
for them both, the shoreline distant but in
his sights.
Moving forward, he turned his head as much
as the weight and struggle would allow, hoping
for a flash of blond safely at the sandbar.
He saw nothing.
On the shore, he called as loud as he could
for help. He set Evie on the sand, brushing
back her curls, ear to her mouth.
No breath.
He rolled her over and pounded on her back.
Salt water streamed from her lips and nose,
dribbling onto the beach.
People came then. Men from the docks, women
from the sea lane. They crowded around, speaking
in whispered tones about the girl. They never
had nice things to say about her, even with
her this way.
The boy told the men that there was one more.
Pointed them toward the sandbar and empty
waves. Barked orders of rescue. The men listened.
Because of the boy’s name.
The boy blew air into the girl’s lungs and
pounded her on the back again, moving her
hair out of the way to make more impact. More
water came forth, this time in a great gush,
along with the rasp of a breath.
Her eyes blinked open, dark and worn.
“Nik?”
“Yes! Evie, yes!”
Smiling briefly, he hugged her close then,
even if it was inappropriate, with her bare-shouldered
in her petticoat and him a prince. But he
didn’t care because she was alive. Evie
was alive.
“Anna?” she asked.
They turned their eyes to the sea.
HAVNESTAD THRUMS WITH ENERGY.
The brightness of summer and the thrill of
Urda’s festival combine to create the kind
of charge one usually witnesses with a coming
storm. It has me up early, feeling light and
free after such a black night.
As I walk down to the harbor, amethyst in
my pocket, I see Nik’s carriage pass by.
I wave my hand, but I can’t tell if he’s
seen me. He’s surely headed into the valley
to visit the farmers in his father’s stead,
a Lithasblot tradition. We give thanks to
Urda but also to those who work our fields.
The ships in port are empty, but I run my
closed palm along their lengths, spelling
them though they won’t be headed anywhere
this day or the next. On a morning as glorious
as this one, it is not hard to conjure the
words for Urda, yet I can’t help but think
back to Nik’s speech. No magic can trick
her. No words can ply her. No will can sway
her. Is my spell a trick? A panic suddenly
seizes me. My heart beats fast and my feet
feel like lead. The dock begins to spin before
my eyes. Is this my punishment? I close my
eyes to right my balance. I’m being silly.
My magic is not meant to deceive. My words
are intended to honor Urda, honor her sea.
Bring life. Surely she knows that. My heart
rate starts to slow and I leave the docks.
I need a distraction.
Nik isn’t supposed to return from the farms
until midafternoon, and while the streets
will soon be alive with festival visitors,
the real party doesn’t get started until
suppertime, when Nik will have to judge the
livestock. So I walk down Market Street and
gather a late breakfast, paid for on Father’s
account—fat strawberries, a stinky half-wedge
of samsø, a jar of pickled herring we call
slid, and a crusty loaf of rye bread so dense
it could pass as a sea stone—and return
to the Havnestad Cove.
It’s quiet here, just a few couples trailing
along the rocks, none taking any notice of
me. I remove my shoes and stockings and place
them in the same spot as yesterday, and I
hop between the smaller footstep islands to
the big one, Picnic Rock earning its name
yet again. The strong sun and calm tide has
made the rock almost completely dry, so I
lie on my back, face to the sky, and shut
my eyes.
Though I don’t want it to, my mind shifts
to Iker. He still hasn’t returned. I am
already anxious, and the same panicky feeling
quickly returns.
What if something’s gone wrong?
What if the steam stack exploded?
What if the whale crashed into the ship’s
hull upon capture?
Am I at fault?
I know I’m being ridiculous, but worst of
all, we would never know. All of us are here,
for once our eyes inward instead of turned
to the sea.
That sends my mind into a downward spiral
about Father, and then suddenly a shadow falls
across the backs of my eyelids, the direct
sun blotted out by a passing cloud. It’s
as if the weather worries too—
“Excuse me, miss?”
That voice.
My eyes pop open, searching for the face of
a friend who I know in my heart is long gone.
But there, leaning over me, is the girl.
The girl from the porthole.
The one who rescued Nik.
Yet that can’t be right, either. I really
am losing my senses today.
I sit up and rapidly blink my eyes in the
sun, but when they refocus, the same girl
remains. She shifts back, long blond hair
swinging.
Her face is like the singsong of her voice—so
much like Anna’s, but more mature. The smattering
of freckles around her nose is familiar too.
She wears a gown that’s nicer than all of
mine put together, and her shoes shine with
new leather.
Shoes. Feet. No fin—she can’t be what
I saw. My stomach sinks, but I don’t know
why.
“This is quite embarrassing, but . . .” The
girl’s eyes fall to the strawberry in my
hand. “I haven’t eaten in more than a
day.”
I’m so stunned, I just hand over the strawberry.
She isn’t ready for it and bobbles it in
her fingertips before taking a bite. I shove
my whole meal toward her.
Anna loved cheese and fruit.
“Oh, no, you don’t have to, I—”
“I insist,” I say, and I’m surprised
that’s what comes out because there are
so many other words on my tongue. So many
questions. But I’m almost terrified to ask
them because I know what word will fall out—Anna.
The girl eats, and I try to figure out what
to say next.
Did you save Nik?
Were you a mermaid?
Are you Anna?
Don’t you remember me?
All would make me run if I were her. So, as
she chews a hunk of rye bread, I open the
jar of slid.
“Do you feel better?” I ask.
“Yes, much. Thank you. I’m so sorry. I’m
done.”
I shake my head and tilt the open jar toward
her, the little herring bobbing in their brine.
“Eat, please.”
She sees the fish and recoils, waving her
hands in front of her face. I pull out a herring
and eat it myself, yanking the bones out by
the tail before discarding them into the cove.
She looks at me as if I’ve just bitten off
her ear.
I used to do the same thing to Anna. She didn’t
like slid either. I smile, but on the inside,
the sadness is suffocating. I have to stop
looking for the dead in the living.
“Are you sure you aren’t still hungry?”
I try. “There’s more cheese.”
“No. I’ll be fine.” A sob swallows the
word fine. Her brow furrows and the skin under
her lashes reddens; there are no tears, but
she looks exactly like she should be weeping.
My hand flies to her shoulder to comfort her.
When the girl catches her breath, she begins
talking again, her voice almost a whisper.
She doesn’t seem to mind me touching her.
“I ran away from home.”
“Oh, Anna—”
The girl’s eyes fly to mine. “Annemette.
How’d you—”
“I didn’t . . . I just . . . you remind
me of someone I used to know.”
She coughs out a sob-laugh. “I wish I were
that girl.”
“No you don’t,” I say quickly as this
girl—Annemette—wipes her nose.
“Was her father a liar? Weaving tales about
where he’s been and what he’s done, selling
off all our livestock and not bringing a coin
home?”
I shake my head because I don’t know what
to say.
“I’ve had to sell half our fine things
to pay his debt and put food on the table.
I couldn’t take it anymore. I took off running
over Lille Bjerg a day ago.”
Her words are off. They seem forced. I can’t
help it—I stare at her face. I’ve seen
thousands of faces since Anna failed to surface,
but I’ve never seen one so similar. Never
heard a voice with the same timbre. If I hadn’t
touched her, if this girl weren’t clearly
made of flesh and bone, I’d think she was
a ghost.
She scrubs her face with her hands, nails
clean and shaped. Her eyes blink open and
then she takes my hands. “I’m terrible.
Here I am, barging in on your breakfast, stealing
your food, dumping my problems in your lap,
and yet I haven’t even asked your name.”
“It’s Evie,” I reply.
“Evie,” she repeats, testing my name out
on her tongue. “British?”
“Evelyn, yes. My mother fell in love with
the name in Brighton.”
“I can see why.” Annemette smiles, her
teeth clean and straight, like that of a princess
or a dairymaid.
I tell myself again that she’s not Anna.
She’s not even the girl from the porthole
or the beach or anywhere else. She’s a farm
girl from the other side of the pass. My cheeks
grow hot. Annemette squeezes my hands. “Thank
you for your generosity, Evie—it’s a gift.
Truly.” Her eyes sting red again and her
lip trembles. “I doubt I’ll be so lucky
again.”
I don’t know what to do with this openness.
This odd feeling blooming in my stomach. “You
really have nothing and nowhere to go?”
Annemette waves her hands across her body.
“Only my clothes and my pride.”
I can’t explain this girl or my feelings
or why I have the need to believe her, but
I do. And I want to help. “Come with me.”
THE LITTLE HOUSE THAT MY FATHER BUILT ISN’T
THAT far from Havnestad Cove—it’s practically
waterside itself, the cottage at the end of
a lane in the shadow of Øldenburg Castle.
It backs up to a thatch of trees that buffer
it from a rocky cliff jutting out into the
sea.
“It’s so quaint,” Annemette says.
“It’s home,” I answer, and push through
the front door. It’s been a long time since
I’ve introduced someone to our tiny cottage.
When I was little, we’d often take in children
while their parents were away at sea. But
that stopped after Mother died.
At the hearth, Tante Hansa is stirring something—by
the smell of it, most likely the ham-and-pea
concoction she brings to every Lithasblot
to place beside the roast hog we have on the
second day of the festival. Because “there
can never be enough swine in this sodden fish
market.” Hansa’s back is turned, and I
feel the need to announce that we have company—it’s
never safe for a witch to have no warning.
“Tante Hansa, I’d like you to meet my
new friend.”
Hansa wipes her hands, and I know by the set
of her shoulders she was stirring the soup
without a spoon. Domestic spells aren’t
spectacular, but they’re her favorites because
she’d never planned on having a family of
her own—and Father and I are more work than
she’d like to admit.
When she turns, her face is pulled up in a
smile, clear blue eyes flashing with the delight
of catching me at something remotely unusual.
Hansa is my mother’s older sister by almost
two decades, the time between them filled
with brothers who lost their lives to the
sea’s moods much too young. She is as old
as the grief of burying all her siblings suggests.
But I have never been able to put anything
past her.
Which means her reaction to Annemette is the
same as mine. Only she actually says what
she’s thinking.
“Why, Anna, returned from the deep, have
we?”
Annemette’s mouth drops open as if she’s
lost her tongue, her jovial attitude gone
as well.
“Annemette, Tante,” I correct. “She’s
from the valley. A farm.”
Hansa takes a step forward and raises a brow—quite
the feat given the blood-drawing tightness
of her hairdo.
“Is that so?” Hansa looks her up and down.
“Those hands haven’t seen a day of hard
work in all your years. That fair face hasn’t
seen the sun. And that dress is worth more
than the best cow in the valley.” She takes
a step forward and grabs Annemette’s smooth
hand. “Who are you really?”
“Tante, please, leave her be, she’s had
a rough trip—”
“Hush. You only see what you want to see.”
She turns back to Annemette, staring at the
girl as if she could bend her will as easily
as she tamed the soup. “So, again I ask—who
are you really?”
Annemette’s eyes have gone red around the
rims again, but she doesn’t cry. If anything,
there’s an edge of defiance in the cut of
them. Like she’s accepted Hansa’s dare
for what it is. But when she speaks, she says
the last thing I’d expect.
“Your soup is boiling.”
But the soup is more than boiling. The pea-green
liquid hisses as it rolls in violent, unnatural
waves over the iron pot’s rim.
“Ah!” Hansa cackles. “I’ve seen your
type before.”
I’m stunned. Her type? Is Annemette a witch?
I stare at her.
Another witch. My age. Next to me.
Of all the things I can’t believe about
Annemette, this might be the most unfathomable.
Something cracks open in my chest as the secret
we’ve held so tightly as a family flies
into the soupy air. I stare at this face so
familiar and yet so strange, and my mind whirls.
Anna was not a witch, but Annemette certainly
is.
Annemette nods, and the liquid returns to
a gentle simmer.
My aunt’s spotted hands grasp Annemette’s
again, but this time there’s a funny light
in her eyes, all her skepticism gone. “Evie,
child, you’ve made quite an interesting
friend indeed.”
It’s a long while before Tante Hansa allows
us to escape, having thoroughly quizzed Annemette
on her family. In the funny way of things,
we both claim lineage to the town of Ribe
and Denmark’s most famous witch, Maren Spliid.
Tied to a ladder and thrown into a fire by
King Christian IV 220 years ago, she became
as much a lesson as a legend. Her talent was
inspiring, but ultimately her audacity was
her undoing. Her death and so many others
under the witch-hunter king scattered Denmark’s
witches like ashes in the wind. And our kind
never recovered—our covens fractured, magic
kept to families and never shared.
Given the time and distance, it shouldn’t
be a surprise that there’s more than one
magical family in Havnestad related to Ribe
and Maren, yet I still can’t believe it.
We’ve been alone for so long.
After Hansa is finally satisfied with her
family tree, Annemette and I head outside.
We walk into the woods behind the cottage,
where we’re shaded from every angle, including
from Øldenburg Castle and its sweeping views,
and start to pick our way down toward the
sea.
The ground is covered in gnarled roots and
branches, a danger for anyone not looking
where they’re going. But I know this steep
path better than anyone, and I use this moment
to steal another glance at Annemette. Her
family may be from elsewhere, but her face
still belongs here.
Anna did not have any magic in her blood,
at least as far as I know. She had two “common”
parents and a grandmother who loved her more
than the sun. Her parents left shortly after
Anna’s funeral. Took their titles and moved
to the Jutland—miles and miles from this
place and the daughter they lost. Her grandmother
is still here, but she’s gone senile with
grief, the loss of her family too much for
her mind. I see her at the bakeshop sometimes,
and she calls every person there Anna. Even
me.
“What?” Annemette says, catching me looking
as we pass between twin trees, slick with
sap.
I can’t tell her what I’m thinking, but
I do have questions for her. “It’s just
. . . how did you know we were witches? If
you’d been wrong, we could’ve reported
you. You could’ve been banished.”
She dips her head to avoid a branch. “I
could just feel it.”
Like Tante Hansa did.
“I must not be much of a witch,” I say.
“I couldn’t tell. I mean, now my blood
won’t stop singing, but an hour ago? No.”
There’s so much I don’t know about the
magic in my bones.
“I’m sure you’re a fine witch, Evie.”
It’s a nice thing to say, I suppose, but
not necessarily true. Tante Hansa teaches
me only the most mundane of spells. But I
read her books and Mother’s books, and I
know there is so much more. With a few words
and her will, Annemette brought out all that
possibility into the open.
“How did you do that? The soup, I mean.”
Annemette just shrugs and hooks a hand on
a tree, swinging around it like a maypole
ribbon. “It was just an animation spell,”
she says as if impressing Tante Hansa was
nothing.
The ease, the comfort, the understanding she
has about her magic makes my blood tingle
with envy. It’s so much of what I want.
It took me months of studying and toying to
create the spell to combat the Tørhed and
even then, I’m not sure it actually works.
My evidence is only anecdotal, and Fru Seraphine
has taught me better than to use anecdotes
as true measures of success.
In a few more steps we reach the sliver of
rocky beach blind to Havnestad Cove, my own
shortcut to Greta’s Lagoon. I try to calm
my heart from beating so loudly, but I’ve
never gone to the lagoon in daylight and I’m
nervous. I steal a glance up the beach. It’s
deserted as far as I can see, everyone off
preparing for tonight’s festivities.
“Careful,” I say as we reach the end of
the beach and the two large rocks. “The
water is deep here.”
I take off my stockings and shoes and wade
in. As I reach the sand, I turn around, but
she’s still standing by the rocks. “Here,”
I say, wading back out and extending my arm.
“Take my hand. I’ll help you.”
With tentative steps, she walks forward and
grasps my hand tight. I smile at her. “Come
on. It’s okay.”
Once we’re in the right spot, I push aside
the small boulders that obscure the entrance
and steer her inside. Although it’s daylight,
the cave is still steeped in shadows. I light
a candle. Various mundane tools hang from
juts on the wall, and on the floor, oysters
sweat in a bucket—my latest failure. On
a ledge in the rock wall are my tinctures,
bottles full of octopus and squid ink, jellyfish
poison, and powdered crab shells.
“You’ve made a lair.”
I laugh. “‘Secret workshop’ might be
a more accurate term.”
“Oh no, this is a lair.” Annemette’s
hands move automatically to the ledge. She
holds each bottle up to the light, admiring
the slosh or swoosh of the contents.
Her boot nudges the oyster bucket. “And
what are your plans for these little fellas?”
She scoops one up and holds it in her hand
as if it’s a baby bird and not an endless
source of frustration for me.
“They’re barren, but I’d hoped to spell
them into producing pearls to be crushed for—”
Annemette stops me cold with a wave of her
hand. She mumbles something I don’t understand
under her breath, her eyes intent on the oyster
in her palms.
Within moments, the oyster swells to a pink
as vibrant as the sunset and springs open.
Inside is the most gorgeous pearl, perfectly
round with an opalescent shimmer.
“It’s beautiful,” I say, though the
word doesn’t do it justice. It’s otherworldly,
unnatural. I want to touch it, but I’m frightened
of it all the same. It seems . . . alive.
Annemette’s grin grows mischievous. “Too
beautiful to crush, I think.” With a simple
Old Norse command—“Fljóta”—she sets
the pearl afloat over her palm. Then, without
saying a word, she commands a few lengths
of thread—repurposed and therefore unspooled—from
the nails on the wall. Next, she covers the
thread and pearl with both hands, shielding
from me the magic she’s clearly working
with her mind, her eyes set on her work. Seconds
later, her hands part to reveal a perfect
pearl necklace.
“Turn around and pull up your hair,” she
says.
I do as she says and she draws the thread
around my neck, draping it so that the pearl
lies at the base of my throat. I don’t own
any real jewelry and have never even tried
any on, save for my mother’s wedding band—Father
keeps it tucked away in a little chest, along
with letters and drawings and other tokens
from their life together.
I touch the pearl and look up at her, but
she is busy working on another oyster and
more string. After a few moments, Annemette
ties her own pearl necklace around her throat.
“And now we match,” she says.
My throat catches. I remember Anna saying
those words to me that time we made necklaces
from wooden beads the tailor was giving away.
They were crude and childlike, yet still special.
We promised to never take them off, but I
couldn’t bear to look at mine once Anna
was gone. It’s now in a small box underneath
my bed.
I force a smile at Annemette. My pearl sits
in cool repose against my neck, pulsing with
vigor. It’s a curious feeling that is not
altogether pleasant, and I wonder if the pearl
will always beat like this. Oddly, I find
myself hoping that it will.
“Can you teach me?” I ask, the words spilling
from my lips.
“What is there to teach? You’re a witch,
aren’t you?”
“I . . . Tante Hansa hasn’t taught me
anything like that. Everything I know is like
a recipe to make cheese—fail one segment
and the whole thing falls to curd.”
Annemette scrunches her nose. “It shouldn’t
be that hard.” She picks up an oyster. “Here.
Try. Fljóta.”
Annemette sees the reluctance cross my face
and tilts her head. “It’s just a command.
Say it with confidence and you’ll have the
magic do the work.”
With hesitant fingers, I take the oyster in
my hand. It’s as gray and barren as ever,
and stinky, too, a tinge of rot to it. “Fljóta.”
The oyster shakes in my fingers but doesn’t
lift. I can’t seem to make that connection
like I do when I spell Father’s ship. There’s
something missing.
“You control the magic, Evie. It’s yours.
Take it.”
There’s a note in her voice that’s like
a jolt—like pushing me off the dock and
into the water.
I square my shoulders and stare at the frustrating,
rotting little thing. I feel my mother’s
blood deep inside me. The blood of Maren Spliid.
The blood of the stregha hiding within my
father’s “common” façade. I feel the
spirit of Urda, outside, inside, all around
me, creating the natural energy we draw from.
I spin these feelings with all the want inside
me—the want to have the sort of power that
could’ve saved Anna and my mother. The kind
that can truly end the Tørhed for good, not
just mask it with a daily spell. The kind
that Annemette seems to have.
“Fljóta,” I say with all that want. With
the wound that lives deep in my belly from
the day I lost Anna. The day I almost lost
Nik too. When I wanted more than anything
to use my magic to make it better.
The oyster hovers.
“Líf,” Annemette whispers. Life. I should
give it life.
“Líf,” I command. The oyster begins to
change colors, its gray shell warming to pink
and then to the burnt orange of dawn.
The oyster grows hot. Hot enough to match
its new lively color. Its warmth licks at
my palm.
In a moment, the oyster pops open, the most
perfect pearl at its center.
It’s beautiful. Again, it’s almost too
beautiful to crush for the magical poultice
I’d planned, but there’s so much magic
I now want to make with it.
Annemette laughs. “And that, my friend,
is how you command the magic.”
Although the spell is over, I can still feel
the magic pulsing through my veins, a blue
fire so hot, it’s cold. It’s unlike anything
I’ve ever felt before. I don’t want it
to stop, but I know there’s a danger in
sipping from this feeling too long.
I set the oyster on the table I use for my
inventions, fashioned from a piece of driftwood
I found on the beach. It’s littered with
more bottles and vials, but I clear some space
and hold the pearl in my fingers. Unlike the
pearl Annemette made, this one is still warm
to the touch, not icy hot. The magic responds
differently to the two of us, I suppose—I
don’t know. But I want to learn.
It’s time I really embrace who I am. Tante
Hansa has kept me in the dark for too long.
My mother was an established healer by my
age.
“Annemette, will you stay and teach me?”
I ask.
“I can’t,” she replies quickly, her
mouth drawn tight, but trembling. She turns
and braces her arms against the cave’s opening,
watching the tide come in and out.
But I don’t understand. Why is Annemette
so upset? Why must she suddenly leave?
“You can stay,” I insist. “You’re
safe here from your father, and we have more
than enough room. And you’ll be with us.
With a family that cares for you and understands
you. You don’t have to run away to find
that. To be yourself.”
Annemette meets my eyes with a look I know,
and with every force of a Viking spell, she
says it again.
“I can’t.”
She bends down and runs her hands through
the sand, letting it fall between her fingers.
“I can’t stay here.”
It’s her. I can’t deny it now. She’s
not trying to deny it either. The look she
gave me is the one I saw on the beach. The
one that I saw on the girl’s face as she
loomed over Nik. Before diving into the water
and disappearing, only a tail fin popping
up from the waves.
“You can’t stay,” I say.
She nods, her eyes nervous.
“You’re not a witch, are you?”
She shakes her head no.
“You’re a mermaid.”
“HOW IS HE—THE BOY?” ANNEMETTE SWALLOWS
HARD and takes a step toward me.
I instinctively take a step back, bumping
into the table behind me and knocking a corked
vial of octopus ink on its side. I’m not
sure if it’s Tante Hansa’s old wives’
tales telling me to run or the fact that Annemette
is clearly more powerful than any folktale
could have ever described. My hand reaches
out and grasps the vial before it rolls and
smashes to the floor. The pearl at my neck
throbs. I want to leave, but her face looks
pained, and I can see now that she’s been
holding this question in since she arrived.
I realize she’s not here for me or my magic.
She’s here for Nik.
In my stunned silence, Annemette goes on.
“Is he all right? He was breathing when
I brought him ashore, but I didn’t have
time to—you came and then that man, and
I had to go. I need him to be alive, Evie.
Please, say something!”
I nod. “He’s fine. You saved him.” My
throat tightens and tears sting my cheeks.
If it wasn’t for Annemette, I’d be dressed
in mourning clothes. “He’s totally healthy.
Strapping. Probably milking a goat at this
very moment!”
Annemette practically collapses in my arms.
“Oh, thank goodness! When he fell into the
sea, I caught him, but the tide and the storm
was so strong, I—”
“Stop. I shouldn’t know,” I say. “You
shouldn’t say any more. It’s too dangerous
for me to—”
“But you aren’t any more welcome here
than I am,” she says, pulling herself upright.
“Your magic is just as forbidden as mine.”
And when my eyes meet hers and they’re clear
and hard, I realize we’ve made an exchange.
A dangerous one.
I know her secret and she knows mine. Breaking
this trust would ensure our mutual demise.
I slip the vial of ink I’d been clutching
into my dress pocket.
We will only survive our secrets together.
“I promise I won’t say a thing,” I assure
her, a hint of regret in my voice.
“Thank you,” she says. “My lips are
sealed too.” She weaves a slim finger through
her blond hair, twisting a long wave into
a curl. “What’s his name—the boy?”
“Nik. His name is Nik. And he’s my best
friend. I’m so glad that you were there.
I saw the wave too late, and he was gone.”
I realize for the first time that after saving
Nik over and over again, even if it was only
on the dance floor, there was nothing I could
have done that night. That he’d have saved
me from the sea, but I would have failed him.
My smile falters and I look down to the gray
oysters at our feet. “I wish I could repay
you with more than a few scraps of food and
a pearl necklace.”
Annemette loops a finger in mine. It feels
strange, too close, but I don’t want to
push her away. “I didn’t do anything special,”
she says. “Mermaids are not the monsters
you humans think we are. I could not just
let him drown.”
Drown. Like Anna did. Like I thought Anna
did.
At this moment, Annemette looks so pretty.
So innocent. She raises her eyes to meet mine.
“Would you like to meet him?” I ask.
“Please,” she says.