I ask.
“Please,” she says.
We leave my “lair” and make our way back
through the rocks, Annemette still nervous
as she heads out first. So strange and sad
to see a mermaid afraid of the sea. As I go,
I pause in the water for a moment—I want
to take a last look at the cave to make sure
all is hidden—and that’s when I feel them.
At my feet, three dead minnows bounce between
my ankle and the boulder—surely knocked
out of the sea by a wild wave and smacked
into the rocks. I shake my head, remembering
the last time such fish floated at my feet,
but I can’t think of that day. Not now.
On the shore, Annemette and I dry off and
put on our shoes. Then we head back up the
trail through the forest. Once the trees spread
out enough and we have room to walk side by
side, I feel as if I can finally ask her more.
“So, have you always been a mermaid?”
Annemette gives me a look. “Have you always
been a girl?”
“Yes,” I reply. “But you’re no longer
a mermaid. At least, I don’t see a tail.
Perhaps you weren’t one from the start.”
She laughs, and I almost draw back because
she sounds just like Anna again. Our elbows
bump as I check myself, wishing I’d just
asked her directly what I wanted to know.
“Sorry to disappoint you,” she says. “Born
a mermaid, hopefully not forever one.” She
dances gracefully into an arabesque pose.
I stop walking. My brows pull together. My
courage rises. “But is it possible, for
a human to drown and become a merperson?”
She shakes her head and I reset.
“How long can you stay like that?”
Annemette glances down for a moment and then
her eyes are up and locked with mine. “A
few minutes,” she says, her back leg still
high in the air.
“No, I mean, how long can you stay human?”
Her eyes shift at the word. She stands up
straight and stretches. “Not long,” she
says after a pause. “At least not as I am.
But it depends.”
“Depends on what?” I push back.
“I promise to tell you,” she says, though
I can see in her hesitation that she doesn’t
quite trust me. Her face turns pale and she
almost looks scared—lost, even. “It’s
just that I have to see Nik first, or none
of it will matter.”
The little pearl pulses against my neck—líf.
Her magic is strong, but good. She saved his
life. The least I can do is make an introduction.
I glance quickly at the sun on its descent
toward the mountains. “We should get going.
The Lithasblot festivities will start soon,”
I say. “It’s our harvest festival. People
come from all over. They’ve even heard of
us in Copenhagen, I swear.”
“Sounds fun,” Annemette says. “And Nik
will be there?”
I nod yes. If she tries anything, I have Tante
Hansa’s and my mother’s magic in my blood.
She grasps my hand tight.
“Let’s go.”
When we come upon the beach where tonight’s
festivities are, the palace staff and some
local villagers are still setting up. We’re
a little early. The livestock stage is being
nailed together, and a hundred or so people
are milling about fixing decorations, laying
out food, and tending the bonfire, where soon
a giant hog will be trussed up on a spit.
“It’s not Copenhagen, but it is a kingdom,
I suppose. As the sun goes down, the beach
will be so full you can barely see a grain
of sand.”
“We have some pretty good parties on the
sand where I come from too.”
I laugh. “I’m sure you do.”
Suddenly Annemette walks up to the fire and
holds out her hands. I forget that she’s
never seen fire like this before.
“Whoa there, young lady,” says Herre Olsen,
the tailor, pushing Annemette back before
I can get to her. “Any closer and you’ll
soon be roasting with the hog.”
“Thank you,” Annemette says with a curtsy.
“I’m sorry.”
“Who are you here with?” he asks.
“I’m visiting for the festival with—”
“Me,” I interject, steering her away from
the scowl on the tailor’s face. “Thank
you, Herre Olsen.
“We need to give you a better backstory,”
I whisper, guiding her toward the castle grounds.
The townspeople like to talk, especially about
me, but the king and queen will need something
substantial if their son is going to be seen
speaking to her. A lowly girl without a house
name is not good enough; I would know.
We decide to give her the title of a baron’s
daughter, the same title Anna had: friherrinde.
A friherrinde from far away—Odense—come
to see our unusual Lithasblot. Her chaperone
has fallen ill, and Tante Hansa is tending
to her. I’m filling in as her chaperone
and guide. Yes. It’ll work. Another lie
added to the list. I suppose there’s some
truth behind the town gossips whispering that
I spread falsehoods, saying the prince should
not trust me. But telling the truth to gain
their approval is not a risk I’m willing
to take.
“When will we see Nik?” Annemette asks,
tired of reciting her story to me.
“Don’t worry.” I point to the giant
stone monstrosity on the hill. “He’s waiting
for me up there.”
Annemette follows my finger.
“Øldenburg Castle,” I say. “Five hundred
years old and as drafty as a sailboat.”
I guide her to the queen’s garden, which
is rich with tulips of every color. Annemette
proclaims each one the most beautiful thing
she’s ever seen until she gets to the next
one. And the next. “I love to garden,”
she says.
Her mouth drops with a gasp when we get to
the queen’s pride and joy—statutes of
her family, each taller than a horse, circled
up among the tulips. The king and queen are
fashioned as they were on their wedding day,
the marble smooth and glistening from the
years. And there, next to them, is the latest
version of Nik—eleven feet tall and chiseled
as if lunging across the bow of a great sea
vessel.
“Is that . . . him?”
She stands on her tippy toes, fingertips not
even getting so far as his tastefully unbuttoned
collar.
“Yes, yes, that’s him.”
“He looks different than I remember. Drier,
I guess.” She laughs.
We crest the steps and there, already waiting
and watching Havnestad Harbor, is Nik. He’s
freshly washed after his trip to the farms,
the light crown he’s forced to wear for
festival days pressed down over his wet hair.
I always think he looks ridiculous all fancy
in Havnestad’s customary blue-and-gold suit,
but Queen Charlotte is from the fjords up
north and very traditional. She insists he
emulate his official portrait for the high
holidays of the Old Norse.
“Evie, there you are,” he says, catching
me first in his line of sight as he turns
from the view. When his eyes land on Annemette,
his face freezes on her features. All except
his lips, which are still moving ever so slightly.
“And you’ve brought a friend . . .”
I smile and guide her toward him. “Your
Royal Highness, this is Friherrinde Annemette.
Annemette, this is Crown Prince Niklas.”
A light zips through Nik’s eyes as he meets
Annemette’s gaze. At first I think that
he recognizes her—that he instantly realizes
she’s the one who saved him. Or that he
sees the old friend we lost, the first half
of this girl’s name ringing in his ears.
But almost immediately it’s clear that he’s
thinking of neither, because he does something
I’ve never seen before. He blushes hard.
Honest-to-Urda heat is rising in his cheeks,
and it’s so intense that he has to glance
at me before looking down.
He thinks she’s beautiful.
And she is—she’s gorgeous—but this . . . this
is unprecedented.
I’m ashamed to admit the pang of jealousy
radiating in my chest. So often, I’m the
only one who has Nik’s attention, and he’s
never looked at me like that. But I suppose
if he had, we wouldn’t be friends. Is this
how he feels when I’m with Iker? Ugh, I
do not want to think about Iker. I smile at
them both, standing awkwardly between them,
wanting to run away but afraid for what might
happen if I did.
“Enchanted,” he says when the words finally
kick in, the blush still hearty along his
cheekbones. “How do you know Evie? I thought
I knew all of her friends.”
I cut in to answer him. “Her chaperone became
ill on their trip from Odense. Tante Hansa
is seeing to her. Annemette very much wanted
to attend a proper Lithasblot festival, so
I’ve become her guide.” I touch her arm.
“And meeting the crown prince is quite the
way to start, isn’t it, Annemette?”
She grins. “Yes, it most certainly is.”
Nik’s color begins to normalize, his training
rushing in on a white horse to rescue him.
His humor, too. “Well, I am quite the carnival
show. Over six feet tall and solid muscle.”
He raises a wiry arm and pats the bicep. “I
have a gaggle of followers trailing after
me like ducklings, just so I can open sticky
canning jars.”
I wink at Annemette. “It’s true; I’ll
have no one else open my troublesome jars.”
There, I’m being a good friend. To them
both. I’m okay with this. Really, I am.
Annemette continues to smile but looks a little
confused. She knows a lot about this world,
but not so much that she might know a canning
jar from a regular one. I smile at Nik and
do my best to save her. “So, are there jars
on the agenda at the moment, Crown Prince
Niklas, or shall we go gawk at some livestock?”
“You really don’t have to call me Crown
Prince Niklas—just Nik,” he says, eyes
on Annemette. “Evie’s just joking. I don’t
care much for titles.” He touches his crown
and then blushes again. “Crowns, either
. . .”
Annemette nods. “What do you care for?”
“Music, mostly.”
“I love to sing.” I swallow as she says
this, my eyes unable to see anything other
than the friend she insists she’s not. The
girl who had the voice of an angel—ask anyone
in Havnestad.
But rather than looking heartsick, Nik begins
to blush again. A sheepish smile spreads across
his face. “Then I shall use my princely
power to borrow an instrument later and accompany
you.”
My stomach churns. This is perfect. Just perfect.
We stroll down the steps and into the garden.
I see him duck away for a moment and pluck
a pink tulip from the end of the row, where
the queen won’t notice it. Annemette dips
down to smell her favorites.
I step away and watch as he strides up to
her lowered form, flower behind his back.
When she stands and turns, he pulls the pink
tulip from where it’s hidden and lowers
into a slight, princely bow.
Annemette’s mouth drops open into a wide
smile and her eyes snap to his.
“Really? I can have it?”
“What good is being a prince if I can’t
pluck a tulip from my own garden?”
“Oh, thank you! This one is my favorite.”
“You are most welcome, Annemette.” Her
fingers snatch it away, and she lifts it to
her nose, inhaling deeply.
When her eyes open, I catch them and smile.
“To the festival, shall we?”
NIK CHOKES DOWN WHAT MUST BE HIS TENTH spandauer,
the flaky sweet pastry sticking to his lips.
As we walk around the festival, Nik is stopped
at practically every turn to taste each table’s
offerings. Whether it’s cheeses both old
and stinky, berries and stone fruit from the
valley orchards, crusty breads of rye and
barley, split-pea delicacies attempting to
rival Hansa’s famous soup, or the tables
and tables of desserts, Nik is required to
try them all. He assures the vendors that
whatever he’s just shoved down his gullet
is the best in all of Havnestad, possibly
in all of the Øresund Kingdoms.
“Save me, Evie,” he grumbles after his
last bite.
Why don’t you ask her? I want to say as
Annemette walks next to me, but instead I
hand him my mother’s handkerchief. “Take
small bites and then use this.”
My mood hasn’t much improved, though I’m
trying. It helps that Annemette’s porcelain
face has gone gray, the seafood our town is
known for churning her stomach. We pass by
tables selling pitch-black whale meat and
pale-pink blubber, lobster bright red and
still warm from boiling, soft-fleshed crab,
salty salmon roe, even slices of slow-roasted
eel.
At the next table, Annemette grabs my hand
and leans into my ear. “Why do you kill
all the sea life if the other options are
so vast?”
I shrug. “It’s our way of life. Havnestad
lives and dies by its nets and harpoons.”
I suppose I should be sympathetic, but it’s
hot, and all this stopping and going has made
me even sourer.
Her brow furrows. “But there is so much
else to eat.”
She leans in, her whisper growing softer as
Nik tries to shake off yet another local culinary
wizard. “My father always tells us to stay
far from the surface, scares us with tales
of our kind being split in two by harpoons,
talks about humans as the scourge of the seas,
always hunting and killing. But this . . .”
“It’s the way it is, Annemette,” I say
as gently as I would to a child. In some ways
that is what she is, even if she’s my age.
The time she’s been in my world can easily
be measured in hours. “We are all surviving
as best we can. We don’t mean harm to the
sea life, or the pig, or anything else.”
“I was unprepared.”
“I was unprepared to meet a mermaid today,”
I whisper, my words just an inch from her
ear. “But I did.”
She laughs into the falling night. Nik glances
over at us, and I raise a brow at him and
purse my lips. He grins at Annemette but then
catches my eye again and I know he suspects
I’m feeding her girl talk. And I’ll just
let him go ahead and think that.
Nik tears himself away from the latest onslaught,
a plate thrust into his hand, fried torsk
dripping with fresh fat, heat rising from
its body, head still on, beady little fish
eyes staring vacantly into space.
“Fru Ulla insists this is the best torsk
in all of Havnestad—possibly all of Denmark,
to hear her tell it. If you seek a true Lithasblot
experience, Annemette, this is where to start.”
I touch the plate and press it toward his
chest, where it is safely out of the way.
“She doesn’t eat fish.”
Nik laughs. “Who doesn’t eat fish? We’re
Danes—”
“Allergy,” I say. “If she has fish,
she’ll blow up like one of those French
flying balloons.”
“It is terrible,” Annemette says, coming
to life and puffing out her cheeks.
The questions die on Nik’s lips. Without
hesitation, he drops the plate into the open
hands of a chubby little boy, who grins wide-eyed
and then hurries after his family. “Then
it will be my sworn duty to protect you from
Havnestad’s affinity for sea life.”
Annemette’s eyes skip to mine and then back
to Nik’s in one swift motion. “The brave
crown prince you are, indeed.”
Long after the fire has died down and the
largest bull from Aleksander Jessen’s farm
has been crowned this year’s winner, Nik,
Annemette, and I sit on the end of the royal
dock, eyes on the ocean and music in the air.
Nik plays a basic rhythm on the guitaren and
Annemette chooses the words—picking old
sailors’ songs that they apparently know
under the sea as well as we do on land. This
one is their play on “Come, All Ye Sailors
Bold.”
“The king trusts to his sailors bold, and
we shall find them as of old—for father,
mother, sisters, wives, we’re ready now
to risk our lives . . .”
I sit beside them with my eyes on the waves,
surprisingly enjoying the clear quality of
Annemette’s voice. It’s as beautiful as
Anna’s ever was, rich and high, with a lovely
air of innocence built into the base of each
note.
“For Danish girls with eyes so blue, we’ll
do all that sailors do. And Dannébrog upon
our masts, shall float as long as this world
lasts . . .”
They are sitting so close together that the
fold of her skirt is touching his trousers.
Neither seems to mind, and if anything, they
drift closer as the minutes pass. I am on
Nik’s other side, and with each song, laugh,
and snippet of conversation, the gap of roughhewn
dock grows between us.
While I’m glad that Nik is happy and that
Annemette seems to have found what she was
looking for, I can’t shake this gray cloud
of self-pity, engulfing me like a fog descending
on the harbor. It was so easy for Annemette
to make that connection with Nik, and no one
thought anything of it. There were smiles
all around as they walked arm in arm, each
townsperson remarking on her beauty, how nice
they looked together. I stalked beside them.
The chaperone.
I know in this moment that I will never find
what they have if I stay in Havnestad. I merely
speak to anyone outside my station and there
are calls to lock me up in the brig. I wish
Iker were here, but it’s clear that even
if he is by my side, it’ll always just be
a childhood fantasy. He may not care what
the others think when he’s with me, but
when it comes down to it, he’ll marry a
highborn daughter, and that will be that.
I will be alone again.
If only Anna were here. The true Anna. Maybe
things would be different.
The tune comes to a natural end, Nik and Annemette
falling into each other in a fit of laughter.
“You have the most lovely voice, Mette,”
he says, using a shortened version of her
name I didn’t know she preferred. I wonder
when she told him to call her that. Or maybe
he just did it, feeling an instant familiarity
with her that I don’t have.
“Much obliged, Nik.” She bends at the
waist. A sitting curtsy. That’s a new one.
“We must do this again tomorrow, Mette.
Please tell me you will be here tomorrow.”
“Yes, yes, of course I will be.” Annemette’s
face beams in the moonlight.
“Excellent. Shall I send a coach round to
your room in the morning? Where are you staying?”
“With me,” I say, the lie we planned ready.
“Her chaperone is quite ill.”
Nik’s brows furrow with concern, or maybe
it’s doubt. He grows quiet for a moment,
and I’d wish he’d speak.
“But then Mette might grow ill,” he says
finally, and I release the breath I didn’t
know I was holding. “And you too, Evie.
You both can stay at the palace. I insist.”
He turns to me, grin in place, though my face
must reflect sheer shock. We’re best friends,
but the line in the sand between us has always
been the palace. I’ve never stayed there—Queen
Charlotte even sent me home the night he nearly
drowned. “I’ll message Hansa and have
your trunks brought round.”
No. That won’t work. Because then he’ll
know Annemette has no trunk—she has nothing
but the clothes on her back. “No worries,
I’ll get them!” I blurt. “Hansa is too
busy to pack her things.”
Nik nods, having gotten what he wanted, the
trunks a mere formality.
Annemette grasps my hands and looks me in
the eye. “Thank you,” she says. There’s
a sincerity in her voice, tinged with desperation
that I haven’t heard since she first asked
if Nik was alive.
Right. She saved him, and she came here to
see him. She had her reasons.
I could kick myself for being so petulant
and bitter all night, even if only I noticed.
But at least I, too, have achieved my aim.
Repaying her good deed with their introduction.
And it seems to be worth a lot to her. To
both of them. Yet still my stomach flutters,
the dock moving as if I’m adrift past the
strait, alone on the open sea.
I DON’T WANT QUESTIONS. I JUST WANT TO GET
UP TO the castle before the queen finds out
about Nik’s invitation. Our lie about Annemette’s
noble heritage passed Nik’s scrutiny, but
he wanted to believe us. His mother, well,
I wouldn’t put it past her to know the name
of every noble this side of Prussia.
At the cottage, I blow through the entryway
like I’ll hurtle through the back window,
through the trees, and off the cliff, but
at the last moment, I veer down the hall and
into my bedroom.
My grand entry does not escape Tante Hansa,
despite the fact that she was surely deep
in her thoughts as she distilled octopus ink
by candlelight.
“Was that a tempest or my sister’s child
bursting through the house?” she asks, coming
down the hall.
I ignore her, shutting my door before plowing
through my chest of drawers for all the proper
pieces of a wardrobe—stays, undergarments,
stockings, boots, dress. I shove in the latest
book of magic I stole from Hansa’s library—Myths
of Maritime—too. There might be something
in there about mermaids that would be worth
a look.
Within a minute, Hansa opens the door. Immediately,
her arms cross and her brows pull together.
“You aren’t going to smuggle your entire
closet out in that trunk, my dear.”
“Who said I was smuggling it?”
Tante Hansa takes a step forward, lips drawn
into a perturbed line.
“The bloomers poking out the front.”
Sure enough, the ruched ankle of an undergarment
is sticking out of my trunk like a dead man’s
tongue.
Hansa tilts her head a bit, one brow now impossibly
raised. “Are you going to tell me why you
are rushing in and out of here with enough
clothes for an entire week at sea? It wouldn’t
have to do with your new friend, would it?”
The thought skips to the front of my mind
to tell her. If anyone would believe that
Annemette is a mermaid, it would be Tante
Hansa. But I can’t tell.
“Well, child? Have you formed the perfect
bluff in your pretty little head? You’ve
had more than enough time.”
“It’s not a bluff. Nik’s asked me to
stay at the castle—Annemette, too.”
That earns me an ancient Hansa chuckle. “His
festival duties have the boy in such a tizzy
that he needs to sleep with moral support
down the hall, does he?”
“Something like that,” I say, though I
know Tante Hansa isn’t buying it.
The brow arches higher. “Are you certain
that cad from Rigeby Bay hasn’t arrived
with promises on his lips and a night’s
lodging at the castle?”
Heat creeps up my cheeks.
In my dreams.
“Iker still hasn’t arrived.” I’m not
sure he will at all, I add in my thoughts,
but I manage to keep my features plain despite
the pang I feel in my chest. “And Nik has
requested my—our—presence tonight in his
stead.”
“Oh, he’s requested, now, has he?” Tante
Hansa peers down her long nose like a blue
heron. “So princely after one canned speech
that he’s now requesting the presence of
his little fish-rat friend?”
“You know Nik’s not like that. Besides,
you come when you’re called—‘Healer
of Kings,’ is it?”
“Don’t make this about me, child. I know
what I’m doing.” She laughs again as I
lug the chest toward the door. Annemette will
be nearly finished with the grand tour by
now. If Nik’s been ratted out by a member
of the staff, the queen won’t go to bed
without addressing him.
“Are you finished with me?” I take a step
toward the door she’s blocking.
“No, I’m not finished with you.” She
crosses her arms for a moment, looking stern,
but then backs away from the door, leaving
a sliver for escape. “But you are just as
stubborn as your mother, and if you fight
me as long as she would have, I’ll be in
this doorway until dawn.”
I take another step toward her and lean in
as much as my belongings will allow, planting
a kiss on her papery cheek.
“Good night, Tante Hansa.”
I stride past her, past her smelly inks, and
out the door. I’m not one step beyond the
threshold when I hear her call, “Don’t
grant all the prince’s requests, darling
girl. Men are always asking for more than
they should.”
Though I’m not with Father on one of his
fish deliveries, it seems too strange to walk
through the main entrance of Øldenburg Castle.
There are some things that are just not for
me as a commoner. Malvina Christensen and
her ilk might think I don’t know my place,
but I do. It’s evident every day.
I’m angling through the tulip garden, the
trunk dragging along at my feet, when I hear
my name.
It’s nearly midnight, but Queen Charlotte
looks just as regal as ever, still in the
full evening gown she wore at the festival,
crown nestled in her perfectly styled hair.
I catch Nik approaching behind her.
“Evelyn,” says the queen, the distaste
in her voice not hard to miss. “Niklas told
me you’d be joining us.” She eyes her
son, and I know he had to fight for me to
stay. “It was gracious of Friherrinde Annemette
to suggest you stay in the same room.”
“She’s very gracious indeed, as are you
for having us, Your Highness,” I say. The
queen nods as if I’ve passed a test—I
know how she prefers to be praised.
“My pleasure,” she says, and steps away.
But then she pauses and turns. “Please stay
within this wing.”
I nod. Yes, I know my place.
Once the queen is gone, Nik rushes to my side.
“Let me help you.”
“I’ve got it.” But just as I say it,
he’s snuck a hand on either handle and hoisted
the thing to his chest, as effortless as can
be.
“You shouldn’t. You’re still recovering!”
“I’m fine. It’s practice for the rock
carry—I have to defend my title.”
“Since when do you care about winning so
much?” I goad him so we don’t have to
talk about his mother.
“Turns out a taste of victory is all I needed
to care.”
“Or the need to impress a girl. Speaking
of . . . where is she?”
Nik takes a step toward the door, and I rush
ahead of him to open it. “Mette was so enamored
with her room; it was so sweet, I didn’t
want to disturb her. Besides, Mother . . .”
His voice trails off as a guard comes to help,
taking the trunk from Nik’s hands. Nik grabs
the edge of the door above my head, relieving
me of my duty. For a moment, I stand there
trying to read his face, because it’s not
as clear and open as I’m used to seeing.
His emotions are all muddled, like Hansa’s
magical ink swirling across the surface of
water.
Nik looks over at the guard. “Take her trunk
to the Baroque Room, please, Oleg.”
Oleg nods, and Nik pulls me back outside and
onto the steps. He sits down on the top step,
and I follow. His shoulder nestles next to
mine and his voice is low.
“Apparently coming of age means more than
giving speeches,” he says without preamble,
his eyes on his hands.
My heart starts pounding and my hand finds
his shoulder. “Nik . . .”
“Mother is pleased because Annemette is
the first of her ‘girls’ to arrive.”
My mouth goes dry. I should’ve seen this
coming—among so many other things these
past few days. Annemette must have passed
the queen’s scrutiny, my aid unneeded.
“She had her ladies send letters to every
high house in Denmark, inviting every princess,
komtesse, and friherrinde to the Lithasblot
Ball and God knows what else. Now that I’m
sixteen, I should be courting, but Mother
thought it wise to bring the girls to me.”
“Oh, Nik—” I start, but then he stares
up at me, and the look in his eyes makes my
throat catch.
“Lured them in with Iker’s presence, too
. . .”
Of course: the playboy prince, two years older,
with brave tales of the sea. I bet every last
girl with a title is on a steamer right now.
“Two princes for the price of one—we’re
the market special,” he says. “No wonder
Iker’s still at sea.”
He’s careful to smile at his joke—he’s
trying to save my feelings. But I can’t
grin back, not even a little bit. I want so
badly to turn to stone like the statues in
his mother’s garden. There must be a spell
for that, no? At least then I wouldn’t have
this rot of disappointment creeping up inside
me. It turns out knowing better doesn’t
always help. It makes it worse.
It’s funny, though—maybe funny isn’t
the right word, but Nik and I are both trapped.
I’ll forever be the fisherman’s daughter,
caught in a web of whispers and lies spread
by those too scared to open their eyes and
see beyond what’s in front of their faces.
And Nik—he’ll be locked in by royal traditions,
forced into a loveless match with someone
only out for the crown. Nik will always be
in the shadow of the castle. And nothing I
can do will save him from that.
Except, if the queen already believes Annemette’s
story, surely Annemette is better than these
komtesses flocking to our shores. She does
seem to make Nik happy. I know it’s only
been a day, but even I’ll admit that I’ve
never seen Nik smile as much as he has with
her. It’s not everything, but it’s a start.
And she’s not after his crown. That I know.
She genuinely cares. She saved him. Besides,
it might serve us all well to finally have
some magic in the palace, to perhaps bring
an end to Queen Charlotte’s brutal warnings
and doll burnings. Maybe as a trusted friend
to both the crown prince and princess, I wouldn’t
be relegated to the kitchen door. My family
would not have to live in secret. If Annemette
makes Nik truly happy, we can both be free.
Stop, Evie. You’re getting ahead of yourself.
But a smile pulls on my lips all the same.
“Let’s go inside,” I say to him. “Everything
will be okay. Annemette is waiting.”
I WAKE IN THE BLUE LIGHT OF THE MORNING AND
SIT straight up. I thought a night in the
royal wing, on the most comfortable mattress
I’ve ever slept on, would do me well, but
it hasn’t. I’m anxious.
I’ve smuggled a mermaid into the palace,
for Urda’s sake!
In the bed across the room, Annemette sleeps,
a ruffle of blond waves piled about her face.
One foot has escaped the bedspread, five toes
stretching lazily toward the ceiling.
It’s easy to forget that she’s never slept
in a bed before. I throw off the covers and
tiptoe to my trunk, left by Oleg next to the
double-sided wardrobe. And there, beneath
my underthings, is the book I threw in at
the last minute. Though the name isn’t too
suspect—Myths of Maritime—I suppose it’s
lucky we arrived so late in the evening that
the maid couldn’t unpack the trunk. I should’ve
been more careful, though.
I crawl onto the plush red window seat and
hold the book up to the new day’s light,
thumbing through the pages for anything about
mermaids. I know all the lore from childhood,
of course. I can still hear Tante Hansa’s
voice reciting the tales over the campfire.
Mermaids call sailors into storms, their siren
songs and beauty too difficult to ignore.
Probably a myth. Annemette is beautiful, but
she didn’t force Nik into the sea, and I’d
be able to tell if she was using magic on
him now. I think.
Then there’s Mermaids can conjure storms
with a blink, sacrificing sailors to please
the all-powerful sea. I hope to Urda that
this is not true. A shiver runs up my spine
as I think of Father and Iker.
But the one that always made me and Anna scream
was: Mermaids steal naughty children and feed
them to the sharks for protection. Ha! I’ll
let Tante Hansa have that one. It kept me
from making lots of unwise choices, though
I suppose not nearly enough. If only Anna
and I had truly listened.
None of this lore is easing my rattled nerves.
The only positive mermaid tale I know is the
one I saw with my own eyes: A kind mermaid
may swim you to shore.
But there has to be more written about mermaids
than a few childhood warnings.
After much reading, I finally find a section
on mermaids, following an intensive discussion
of the kraken. It doesn’t say much—there’s
just slightly more detail than the descriptions
I know by heart. I focus in on one paragraph.
Accounts of mermaids at the surface often
come with tales of rescue—the saved sailor
opening his eyes just as the mermaid dives
back into the waves. The maids are always
described as staying within the water, unable
to leave the sea completely.
That was exactly how it happened. Maybe there
will be more on what happens next. I turn
the page, expecting a section on a mermaid’s
ability to change into human form. But there
is nothing. No description, no account, no
guesses at all.
I stare at Annemette. She can’t be the first
mermaid to change into a person. She can’t.
It just must be so rare there’s not an accurate
tale to pass on.
Possibly feeling the weight of my eyes on
her, Annemette shifts, her arms stretching
high above her head. Her eyes blink open and
she sees me watching her. I expect her to
startle, to forget where she is and what she
is, but she doesn’t. Instead, she just yawns.
“I could get used to this.” She rolls
fully toward me. A slim finger points to her
calf. “But is it normal that this part just
aches? Burns. And my toes are . . . tingly.”
“Pins and needles?” I offer.
“More like knives,” she replies without
hesitation. “But I’ll be fine.” She
pushes herself up a little and yawns again.
I set my book between my nightdress and the
windowpane. “Maybe it’s a side effect.
You know, of your transformation,” I say.
And now’s my chance: “Have other mermaids
ever turned into humans before?”
“I’m not the first,” she replies. She
stands and turns her back to me as she opens
the wardrobe, revealing a closetful of dresses.
“Where’d those come from?” I ask, my
mouth agape as I walk over to the wardrobe.
“I conjured them last night while you were
sleeping.”
I want to scold her for doing something so
reckless, but they’re incredible. Silk day
dresses in pink, cerulean, and deep purple,
each with little white collars and pearl buttons.
I clutch at my necklace and wonder if those
pearls pulse like mine. The evening gowns
are even grander. Full skirts and long trains,
gold embroidery, and even beading. They’re
going to think she is the wealthiest friherrinde
in the whole region.
“Do you like?” she asks. “Hopefully
they will do the trick.”
I nod eagerly. “What trick?”
“Allowing me to stay,” she says, clutching
a Havnestad-blue dress with mother-of-pearl
inlay. “Don’t you want me to stay?”
“Of course I do, Mette,” I say, trying
out the nickname for the first time. And I
realize I mean it. Not only so she can save
Nik from his mother’s misguided intentions,
but to have a friend who knows magic, who
knows the real me. I didn’t know how much
I wanted that until I met her. “How long
do you have?” I ask, hoping she’ll give
me a real answer this time. “I want to help.”
“The magic lasts four full days,” she
replies. “I have three left.”
My face falls. “That’s it?”
“But three days becomes forever if, before
midnight on the final day, my true love has
fallen for me, too.”
Too.
Nik.
Forever.
“I love him, Evie. I really do.” Annemette
flops on the bed, no longer the shifty girl
holding everything back. More like the girl
I used to talk with about boys and gossip
in her own grand room. “He’s why I came
back. I know he can love me. Didn’t you
see us last night?”
“But what if he doesn’t?” I ask. She
turns and stares out the window, out at the
sea far below.
“What is it?” I come to her and sit on
her bed. “Tell me, Mette.”
She shakes her head and buries her face in
her hands. When she responds, it’s as if
she’s repeating something she read in a
book—and maybe she is.
“To come to land in human form a mermaid
must complete a magical contract—her life
as a mermaid for four days on land.” She
pauses and shudders, her chest heaving slightly.
“She may not return to the sea after those
four days, for she can never again be a mermaid.”
My stomach practically tumbles to my feet.
“Wait . . . you die?” What kind of dark
magic did she do? Nik is wonderful, amazing,
the best guy I know—but to risk her life
for someone she barely knows?
She sits up and nods. “I know. It’s crazy.
But you don’t get it. He’s what I’ve
been missing. I knew he was mine when he fell
into the sea. Into my arms. And to be human?
Evie, you don’t know how lucky you are.”
I don’t even know what to think. Of course
I want her to live, and I want them both to
be happy, but how can this work? Falling in
love in four days seems . . . unrealistic,
to say the least.
I temper my words carefully. “How can you
tell when he truly loves you?”
Annemette’s face goes dreamy again. “True
love’s kiss is all I need.”
I almost laugh. Now it’s unrealistic and
ridiculous. So much so, I’m completely incredulous.
“A kiss, really? Your life for a kiss? That’s
it? That’s some magic.”
“It’s the feeling in the kiss. I’ll
know. The magic will know.”
I think of Nik on the steps—enchanted, yes,
but in love? No. Not yet, anyway.
I walk back to the window seat. I need space
to breathe, to think. If Annemette hadn’t
risked her life on this, I don’t know how
I’d feel if Nik really did fall in love
in three days. The whole thing just feels
wrong—her life depending on Nik somehow
awakening powerful magic, simply by having
enough love in his heart for a girl he’s
only just met. One I like, one he likes, one
I’m forever grateful to. But I just don’t
know . . . there has to be another way to
keep her alive without forcing Nik to love
her.
When I look up, Annemette is rushing toward
me. She squeezes onto the window seat beside
me and takes my hands. The color has drained
from her face.
“Evie . . . I’m not encroaching, am I?”
Worry furrows her brow. “You were searching
for him that night . . . he was waiting for
you at the palace last evening. He isn’t
. . . ? You don’t . . . ?”
“I’m not in love with Nik, and he’s
definitely not in love with me.” I’ve
had to say this exact phrase many times, most
recently to Malvina. “We’re just best
friends.”
She breathes out a sigh, hands fluttering
as she smooths her hair. “You seem so close,
and I didn’t even question . . . you must
think I’m horrible.”
“Not at all! Nik and I have been inseparable
for years.” I struggle to make eye contact
here, her closeness again overwhelming. “It’s
a common mistake.”
Relief washes over her, and she sinks back
against the window seat cushions. “Do you
have someone, then? Someone who makes your
heart beat so hard you think it’ll pound
itself out?”
Iker’s face flashes in my memory, a wide
smile reaching the ice of his eyes. I bite
my lip. “I do—I did. I don’t know.”
Annemette is staring at me for more, so I
reluctantly go on. “You saw him—the other
boy on the beach that night.” She nods in
recognition. “Well, he’s Nik’s cousin,
the crown prince of Rigeby Bay. But it doesn’t
matter, Mette. He’s away at sea, and we
have more pressing things to consider. Three
days . . .”
“Oh, Evie, you’re such a good friend,”
Annemette says, pulling me into an embrace.
Three days to fall in love. Three days to
live. Three days until the ball every noble
lady in the Øresund Kingdoms will attend.
I shake my head. Finding true love is hard
enough without the competition.
I DON’T KNOW HOW SHE ACTS SO CALM AS WE
WALK down to meet Nik for breakfast. It must
be the sea in her veins, flowing against the
tide no matter what the weather. My entire
body might as well be one giant bundle of
nerves tied up in a sailor’s knot on her
behalf, but Annemette walks out onto the sun-drenched
balcony off the third-floor ballroom looking
as enchanting and confident as anyone could,
her blue dress casting her eyes a deep ocean
hue and her butter-blond hair shining in the
sun.
We blink into the bright light and are met
with a spectacular view of the harbor. I know
our corner of the sea so well, but it’s
different from this angle, nearly the whole
coast in sight. It’s an empowering view,
to be able to see all that you rule over.
The current is moving faster than usual for
this time of year, and I turn my back, not
wanting to dredge up old memories.
“Good morning, ladies. Won’t you have
a seat?” Nik stands and pulls out the chair
to his right. “Mette?”
Annemette blushes and takes the coveted place.
I push my nerves down and greet him with a
wink as he pulls out my chair. It’s then
that I see he’s a bit red himself, that
blush from last night back again at the sight
of Annemette. Nik, the romantic. A good sign
for sure.
True to his word of protecting Annemette from
the evils of our seafaring diet, Nik asked
the palace kitchens to avoid the traditional
breakfast herring and traded up for summer
sausage, sweet rolls dripping in fresh butter,
and raspberries flush with dew. Served with
it is black tea, hot and fragrant.
My stomach growls at the mere vision of all
this food. It had been churning all morning,
my anxiety getting the better of me. I am
starving.
“Goodness, Evie. Do you have a tiger hidden
in your bodice?” Nik laughs into the delicate
china of his teacup.
“You know me, always smuggling wild animals
to breakfast,” I joke.
“I’d expect nothing less from your dark
magic.” Nik laughs again, and he has to
put the cup back into the saucer to keep from
spilling it over his shirt.
Meanwhile, Annemette can’t hide her surprise.
She stares at me, confused. After all that
fuss I made about how we must keep our magic
a secret here, the crown prince, of all people,
is laughing over it.
“Nik should know better than to spread dangerous
rumors like that.” I gently elbow him. This
is a game we play, Nik and I. Joking about
the “magic” in my family—even if his
joke is closer to the truth than he knows.
“My tante, Hansa—”
“She turns men to toads and makes a soup
out of them,” Nik says, brows shooting dramatically
under his hair. Annemette laughs, which only
encourages him. “It’s a great bit of luck
you didn’t have her pea soup last night.”
Annemette’s lips drop open.
“It’s green for a reason.” I wink at
her.
Nik and I burst into a fit of laughter, and
it feels good to relax. His fingers scramble
to touch the bare skin at her wrist. Maybe
this will work.
“We kid, Mette,” Nik goes on. “Tante
Hansa is a marvel of a medicine woman—she’s
saved my father a few times when our own doctor
failed, and I’ll never forget it. She’ll
take great care of your chaperone—but she
can’t turn men into toads.” Annemette
nods, a quizzical grin pulling up against
her pink cheeks. Nik lowers his voice, conspiracy
thick in his tone as he turns his back on
me. “Though I wouldn’t put it past the
old bat to have curbed my cousin’s playboy
ways so that he might fall for her niece.”
I elbow him again, this time quite hard, and
both he and Annemette laugh. “If she has
that magic, it’s certainly gone awry, considering
he didn’t come for the festival,” I say.
“Surely that’s Iker’s mistake,” Nik
says, snagging a sweet roll.
“I don’t make mistakes, Cousin.”
We glance up. Iker is standing in the threshold,
his back propped casually against the doorframe.
His skin is tan from days spent on deck in
the high sun, making his hair seem more bleached
than usual. He absentmindedly rubs at the
scruff blurring the cut of his strong jaw,
something I’m sure Queen Charlotte will
insist he shave. I hope he declines.
My heart is beating in my throat as he looks
over at me and our eyes meet. He grins.
Don’t smile. Don’t get up. He promised
he’d return days ago. Stay strong.
I cave. A small smile creeps up on my lips
and, in turn, his grin blooms larger. He strides
over, and suddenly I’m afraid he’s going
to kiss me right there in front of everyone.
In front of Nik. He pauses before me and bends
down, his fingers grazing my chin as his face
moves closer to mine.
Please don’t.
Gods, I wish he would.
His lips land softly on my forehead. I breathe
out a sigh, whether it’s relief or disappointment,
I don’t know.
“Hello, Evelyn,” he says, standing upright
again. “I’m sorry I’m late.”
Before I can say anything, he strides over
to Nik, stealing the sweet roll straight out
of his fingertips. “Hello, Cousin. Glad
to see you’re looking so well,” he says,
then takes a bite of the roll.
Nik stands, and the two embrace. “Mother
has been in a royal tizzy over your tardiness—I
hope you found that king whale you were looking
for.”
“I wish,” Iker replies, frustration echoing
in his voice. It’s unlike him not to get
what he wants. “We chased him past the tip
of the Jutland, but he’s a slippery bastard.”
“I suppose that’s why he’s named ‘king,’
Cousin.”
Iker grins and claps Nik on the shoulder.
“We are a slippery lot, aren’t we? Always
running to and from the call of duty.”
“And you are forever running late in both
directions.”
“Nothing that can’t be fixed with a grand
entrance and a daring story.”
I raise a brow. “That certainly is your
life’s motto.” The words come out harder
than I’d planned, and his smile stiffens
in answer.
“I’d say it’s worked well for me so
far.”
“You would,” Nik says. He’s now standing
next to Annemette’s chair, his hand grazing
her shoulder. “But let it be, Cousin. I’d
like you to meet Friherrinde Annemette.”
Annemette stands and steps toward Iker. She
holds out her hand like she’s done this
hundreds of times before. He takes her fingers
in his and kisses them. “Lovely to meet
you, Annemette. I daresay I would’ve remembered
such a gorgeous girl from my travels in the
Øresund. Tell me, where did you wash up from?”
My heart in my throat, I meet Annemette’s
eyes. He’s just being kind, I know he is,
but still.
“Odense,” she says, clearly comfortable
despite my heart flaring out my nostrils.
“Evie and I met yesterday, and she agreed
to show me around. Nik was game enough to
join us.”
“Who wouldn’t be?” he replies. “I’d
say yes in an instant.” Iker smiles at her,
but there’s suspicion in his eyes. It’s
just a flash, but it’s there—he doesn’t
even try to hide it. Nik and I both notice
it before his cultivated manners return and
he bows at Annemette. “I’ve traveled everywhere,
and there are no two prettier girls in all
the world than on this balcony.”
Both Annemette and I immediately flush scarlet,
the compliment the perfect Iker level of grandness.
And, when I glance over, Nik is fiercely blushing
too—his eyes have never left Annemette.
Iker’s attention spins across the three
of us.
“What?” I ask.
Then he shakes his head. “The lot of you
won’t survive your youth if you don’t
learn to take a compliment or ask for what
you want.”
Iker turns to Nik. “Cousin, clearly you
can’t keep your eyes off the girl. Why don’t
you ask the fine friherrinde to accompany
you as you explore today’s festivities?
I’m sure there is plenty to learn about
her.”
Annemette turns to him, a lock of blond hair
twisted around her finger. Nik lets out a
nervous laugh.
Iker, not paying attention, goes on. “While
you’re doing that, Evie and I can walk through
the gardens.”
“Really?” I say. “Don’t you think
you should ask me first?”
“Forgive me, Evelyn. Would you do me the
honor?”
I should say no. After all, what is the point?
In a day’s time, he’ll be dancing with
half the komtesses invited to the ball, one
of whom will surely become his bride. But
I can’t help wanting what I want. I look
up at Annemette, whose eyes are urging me
to go. She needs this time too. Two magical
creatures and two princes. I want to laugh.
Maybe it’s time I stopped accepting what
all of Havnestad has deemed appropriate for
a girl like me and started acting like the
girl they already think I am.
“It would be my pleasure, Iker,” I say,
getting up from my chair.
Nik suddenly stands, looking very uncomfortable,
ears turning red too. “Iker, I don’t think
that’s a very good idea.”
Iker’s eyes brighten and then drop into
the same suspicious glance he gave Annemette.
He reads his cousin’s face and posture,
clearly trying to discern if this is about
him being alone with me or about Nik being
alone with Annemette or something else altogether.
His words from the ship ring in my ears: I
don’t like to step on my cousin’s toes.
“I’m not going to defile the girl, cousin,
we’re just going to have a kiss and catch
up.” Nik practically scoffs, but Iker just
smiles. “Nothing we haven’t done before.”
Nik’s eyes shoot to mine, and I know he
knows. It doesn’t take much for him to picture
all of it—to picture me kissing Iker like
all the other girls he leaves in his wake.
I glance down—I wish it wasn’t like this.
I just can’t take Nik looking so hurt.
Iker makes it a point to raise his brows at
Annemette, everything in the move suggesting
Nik take his girl and be fine with it. A hope
I have as well. The girl only has three days.
Iker’s arm slinks from my waist and hooks
about my elbow. He leads me toward the door.
“Follow my lead, Cousin, but don’t follow
my footsteps.”
The late morning light is blinding when we
step out of the shadow of the castle and into
the queen’s tulip garden. We blink ourselves
down the stone path, stumbling a bit until
our eyes adjust, arms and legs momentarily
touching—whether by accident or on purpose,
only Urda knows.
It’s sinking in. Iker is here.
He came back. And he immediately wanted to
be with me.
All the disappointment and fears about what
was keeping him seem to drain from my body.
I try to push thoughts of Annemette to the
side, too. Not everyone is your responsibility,
Evie—Tante Hansa has told me this a thousand
times. Annemette is alone with her prince,
and I’m with mine.
After years of daydreams, my childhood fantasy
is somehow now my reality: holding hands in
a garden with Iker. Despite my status. Despite
his. Despite the lives that are meant for
us. A flash of heat runs up my neck, and my
cheeks flush with embarrassment. Iker can
never know how often I’ve thought of this.
But is this real? Am I stuck in dream? Or
have I lost my mind completely, and Annemette
is a figment of my imagination? Iker, too?
I wouldn’t think him real at all if his
arm weren’t still slung about my waist,
drawing me toward him, the two of us walking
toward a stone bench beneath a shady oak.
Stop questioning, Evie.
Enjoy the spell while it lasts.
He smells of the sea. Of escape. And I want
to be there with him, watching his skin go
pink and then brown, whales in our sights
and free wind in our hair. He turns to me,
both hands about my waist now, face angled
down toward mine. A smile curves at his lips
as he reads my eyes.
“You were worried I wouldn’t come,”
he says, and brushes a curl from my cheek.
I don’t deny it.
“I ran into a problem of sorts,” he says,
eyes in the middle distance, voice softening.
“I lost one of my men. The sea snatched
him overboard in broad daylight after we docked
in Kalø. Spent the rest of the day and much
of the next searching.”
My breath catches. It’s awful, though not
unexpected on a whaling expedition. The resolute
set to Iker’s jaw mirrors that—disappointment
but also acceptance. But then his gaze brightens
and he goes on. “Eventually, we found him,
floating unconscious between two rocks. Can
you believe it? Barely breathing and beaten
up, but alive. It was so strange, finding
something you doubted could be possible.”
A teasing note then enters his voice. “Just
like you shouldn’t have doubted me.”
“I didn’t doubt you. I doubted my expectations.”
Iker raises a brow and his eyes are on my
mouth. “And what were your expectations?”
“That you wanted to be here as much as I
wanted you to be here.”
At this, he draws me in until his chest touches
my bodice and I can feel his legs through
the layers of my dress.
“Don’t doubt this.”
He presses his mouth to mine, stealing my
breath. He is gentle in that first moment,
but then sweeps us down onto the bench.
The scent of salt and limes swirls about me
as my heart begins to pound hard enough that
I’m sure he can feel it through my bodice
and his shirt.
His hands move to my face, thumbs sweeping
the curve of my jaw. He holds me there for
a second before gently pulling away.
“Proof enough, Evelyn.”
He says it as a statement, not a question,
a sly little grin returning.
I purse my lips in thought. “Honestly, I’m
not sure I’ve had a large enough sampling
to be certain.”
Iker’s face breaks that sly little grin
into something toothy and wolfish.
“I’m free for sampling all afternoon.
Nothing princely planned until supper.”
He forces his features into serious composure.
“Will that be enough time, my lady?”
I lean in and dust a quick kiss onto his lips.
“It’s certainly a start.”
FOUR YEARS BEFORE
The visitor stood on the dock, parents fussing
behind him, weary from travel, though the
journey hadn’t been far. Just across the
Øresund Strait—a trip he could make with
his eyes shut and in his own boat, if given
the chance.
And he was planning to take that chance within
the year, permission or not.
The day was clear, sun beating down, drying
the wooden planks of the dock faster than
the sea could make its mark, the waves angry
the entire way from Rigeby Bay.
Footmen filed down from the castle, whisking
away the visitor’s parents, trunks, and
duties, leaving him alone with the beach and
his thoughts. At fourteen, those thoughts
were mostly of girls.
Brunettes.
Blondes.
Redheads.
All of them swirling in his head despite what
he knew to be true about his station—his
mother and her metaphors constantly in his
ear.
“Tulips wilt no matter their beauty; jewels
of the crown shine forever.”
“Blood lasts longer than a whim.”
“The royal vase has room for but one flower,
no matter the harvest.”
His feet led him to the sand, eyes snagging
on two girls prancing along the beach, slim
forms moving in time with a song that barely
reached his ears.
A few yards more and the girls stopped, eyes
and fingers pointed toward a sandbar, belly
up in the swirling waters. That’s when he
recognized them—two girls from the village,
best friends always up for an adventure, just
like he was, though he got the feeling the
blonde was rather difficult to impress. Trailing
behind them was a boy, his cousin. Another
prince.
Then the girls began to remove their dresses,
petticoats suddenly catching the sun’s rays
in all their angelic white.
He couldn’t look away.
Not when they folded their dresses and laid
them on the sand. Not when they sprinted into
the waves. Not when he realized the current
was as strong as it’d been in the strait,
though he was too distracted by daydreams
of their petticoats to warn them.
It was only moments later, when the prince
dove in behind them, that the visitor was
rudely awakened.
The visitor’s feet told him to run. To help.
Neither girl had surfaced—it had been too
long. He took five steps and halted. His father
in his ear this time, another Øldenburg ruler
in a land full of them.
“Do not be a hero, Iker; you are already
a prince.”
His own kingdom needed him alive. If something
were to happen to him, the future of his home
and his family would be in danger. Yet still,
another voice, his own, knocked around in
his ears.
“But Nik . . .”
His cousin had grown tall of late, at least
six feet already, but he’d seen tulips thicker
than his arms, harpoons wider than his legs.
The visitor was the same height but built
with all the vigor of the Vikings. He was
strong. He could help.
Still, he stayed rooted to the spot. Holding
his breath as his cousin finally surfaced,
a black-haired rag doll drooping in his arms.
Strong and steady, Nik swam for the beach.
As the two landed in the sand, the visitor
breathed again, watching in awe as the boy
of twelve did all the right things to expel
water from her lungs. Citizens gathered around
their prince now, Lithasblot preparations
halted, all of them getting a good look at
the latest near tragedy in a history full
of them, the sea well fed in the whale-wild
Øresund Strait.
All the relief he’d felt fled the second
his cousin began barking orders to the men
standing around, their inaction frustrating
him. The men finally dove into the water,
but Iker knew his cousin. Knew his heart.
Knew what he would do. He was going back too.
These girls had been a part of him for years,
one the left arm, one the right. They were
both beauties—even Nik had admitted it during
his last visit. The raven-haired girl was
more his cousin’s style, but the visitor
knew the blonde was the one who saw Nik in
that way—it was obvious.
The visitor watched the prince dive back into
the waves, and then he ran, all the strength
of his Viking blood carrying him as he tore
across the sand.
He yelled at the men swimming back to shore
empty-handed, soggy from their attempts at
finding the girl. “You there, men, don’t
leave your crown prince to do the dirty work
alone. Back in the water with you—your hope
does not fade until Prince Niklas’s does.”
Immediately, the men turned for the waves,
diving in, hope the last thing set in their
features. Every cut of jaw locked with the
knowledge that this was just how things went
in the Øresund Kingdoms. The sea took as
much as she gave.
But he wanted them there in case Nik faltered.
These men were insurance for the prince. Their
shared family could not suffer this blow,
no matter how heroic.
“Evelyn, are you all right?” He crashed
to her side, palms cupping her elegant shoulders.
“Iker?” She blinked at him as if he were
a ghost, those midnight eyes of hers dark
with terror. “Anna. Nik—”
“I know,” he said in his best prince voice,
the one he’d been perfecting in front of
the looking glass when stranded in the castle,
his heart yearning for the sea.
Iker turned back to Evelyn. Tears welled in
her eyes, gratitude in the curve of her lips.
He knew enough about the girl to know how
she felt about him, how she wanted to kiss
him right there. He knew enough about her
class—the fishermen, the worker bees—to
know that she wouldn’t.
Instead, her fingers tightened on his forearm
as if she were still fodder for the undertow
and he’d rescued her himself.
“It’d kill me to lose either of them.”
She glanced down at her hands as if the answer
were there, hidden in the web of lines—heart,
life, and fate.
“There is so much I wish I could do,”
she said, her voice still so weak.
That was it. There was so much he could do.
Nik was his cousin, true, but he had always
felt like a brother. And no matter the correct
name for their relationship, he was family.
And family did what had to be done.
Iker squeezed Evelyn’s shoulders for the
barest of moments, and then he was gone, yanking
off his boots as he ran toward the foaming
undertow.
“OH, EVIE, IT WAS WONDERFUL,” ANNEMETTE
SAYS after half falling into the window seat
in our room. Her blond waves are as wild as
the tide in a storm, spilling at all angles
around her shoulders. The cream of her face
is flushed with pure joy, deep-blue eyes sparkling.
I’m so happy to see her like this. Iker
and I spent the afternoon swirled together
in a rush of touches and sweet words, two
pebbles in a whirlpool, and I can only hope
that she and Nik did as well.
“Nik is wonderful,” I confirm, but she
grabs my hand.
“More wonderful than I could have ever dreamed,
but so are you. There is no way I would have
had the day I just had without you.” Her
eyes swell, the skin there growing pink.
I squeeze her fingers. “It’s nothing,”
I say, though I can’t imagine the last few
hours with Iker would’ve happened without
her either. I can’t picture him arriving
at the castle and then hiking into its shadow
to find me in the tiny house at the end of
the lane. It’s difficult to imagine grand
Iker confined by a home smaller than this
entire palace bedroom—even when he’s on
his little schooner, his personality still
has room to burst into the open air of the
sea.
“Do you think he’s falling in love?”
I ask as I change dresses for tonight’s
Lithasblot festivities.
“I think so,” she says. “I hope. More
time would help.” She smiles weakly.
“The sooner we get going, the more you’ll
have. Almost ready?”
She fastens up the last few pearl buttons
on her pink silk gown. “Almost,” she says
and then looks at my worn navy dress. “Is
that what you’re wearing?”
I nod. I could probably conjure up a range
of dresses too if I put my mind to it, but
that would really send the town chirping.
Everyone knows what’s in my wardrobe.
“No, no. Wear this,” she insists, and
hands me a deep purple gown embroidered with
golden tulips. “I made it for you. Iker
will love it.”
I take the dress, running the lush silk between
my fingers. “Thank you,” I say. “It’s
beautiful, but I couldn’t. Can you imagine
everyone’s faces? Me in this? What will
the townspeople say?”
“Maybe something nice, for once,” Annemette
replies with a smirk.
I know she’s wrong, but I can barely take
my eyes off the dress. It’s stunning, the
workmanship so intricate, it truly could only
have been achieved with a spell. And then
it hits me. We have magic. “Annemette . . .”
“Yes?” she says, weaving her golden strands
into an ornate bun.
“Can’t you use your magic . . . on Nik?
I mean, only if things don’t go as planned.
He can love you; I can see it. It’s just
. . . three days—now almost two—there’s
no t—”
“No,” she says, sticking the last pin
in her hair. “It has to be real when the
clock strikes midnight after the ball. That’s
it. Magic can masquerade as love, but none
has ever satisfied Urda before. These little
things, dresses and such, are as far as I’ll
go. He has to love me as me. No tricks. Promise
me you won’t do anything to interfere, Evie.”
I nod, my lips closed tight. Of course she’s
right. I don’t want to manipulate Nik’s
feelings either, but the consequences are
just so steep.
I step into her gown, the cool fabric sliding
over my skin, its shape fitting me perfectly.
I barely recognize myself as I stare in the
mirror, looking so much like one of the nobles.
Perhaps a costume is all I ever needed.
“You look like a princess,” Annemette
says, giving me a kiss on the cheek. “Let’s
go. Our princes await.”
I grab her hand, and we walk down through
the palace and out the gates. This night,
the third night, is what everyone always mentions
when Lithasblot comes up. When it is perfectly
normal, possibly even a compliment, to toss
a slice of rye or a dense roll at your neighbor.
Predictably, Malvina Christensen lives for
this night. It gives her a chance to show
off, and gods know she would never shy away
from that. Not one for needlepoint or whatever
komtesses are supposed to learn, Malvina chose
to take up baking instead, always underfoot
of her cook as a girl. I’ll admit, she became
rather good, that blue monstrosity aside,
though I’ll take partial responsibility
for its demise. She’s eager to tell anyone
questioning her that baking is a hobby, even
though it’s beneath her, an activity more
befitting someone like me. “If you feed
a man right, he’ll be true to you for life,”
I’ve heard her say many times. It’s strange,
she so wants me out of her way, too crude
for her class, and yet here she is parading
her lowbrow achievements. I guess when you
have power, you can be whoever you want.
Though the sun has yet to set and the townspeople
are still wandering the offering tables in
search of their suppers, Malvina has snagged
herself a prominent spot by the bonfire. Around
her is a literal sea of treats—petits fours,
scones à la Brighton, out-of-season fried
aebleskiver, and crusty rolls of rye and soft
rolls of sweet Russian wheat, both in the
shape of the sun wheel. There’s a massive
blueberry pie as well, juices glistening from
under a golden lattice crust.
“Malvina, my, you’ve outdone yourself
yet again,” Nik says with a royal smile
as we come upon her.
The girl beams at him. “Why thank you, Nik.
It would be an honor if you enjoyed something
before the throwing begins.”
Nik waves her off. “That’s not—”
“I insist. Please take something, there
is more than enough here for Urda.”
Training and practice with Malvina’s forcibly
charitable nature are enough to keep Nik from
fighting her one word more. “If that is
the case, then yes. Something small would
be greatly appreciated.”
Her still-beaming smile grows larger as she
dips to the blanket and chooses a petit four,
done in perfect French style. “There’s
plenty for your friends, too,” she adds
as an afterthought.
I’m shocked. Malvina has never offered me
anything, and then I realize, she may not
recognize me. It’s the dress. It must be
sewn with the most powerful sorcery to deceive
a shark like Malvina.
“How kind of you,” I say, taking a scone
and watching her pewter eyes for recognition.
And then there it is, a slight snarl.
“Oh, Evie,” she says. “My, that’s
quite a dress. Where did you—”
“It was a gift. From me, Friherrinde Annemette,”
Mette interrupts while plucking a sweet roll.
“For being a good friend and the most gracious
host.” And then she does the unthinkable—she
links her arms right through mine and Nik’s,
pulling us close on either side.
Malvina smiles so tightly I can see the veins
in her neck. “Well, from a komtesse to a
friherrinde, a word of advice. If you treat
your help to such finery, they’ll get used
to it.”
“I hope so,” says Annemette. “I have
plenty more where that came from. Thank you
for the sweets.”
And then we walk away. Just like that. Nik
seems a little stunned, ever the proper prince,
but even he can’t help but laugh. “You
really do look lovely, Evie.”
“Seconded,” Iker says, grabbing my hand.
I thank them both for probably the third time
that night, and then we walk the boys to the
platform for tonight’s celebration of the
grain crop. Annemette and I take our seats
in the little white wooden chairs reserved
for the nobility—another new view for me,
having only sat on the sand before. As the
sky darkens, Nik begins to speak, but I can’t
focus, my mind on so many things. The Lithasblot
festival was always something I knew so well,
every year the same, and for a time, I didn’t
go at all.
The Lithasblot after Anna drowned, I never
left the house. Nik, Tante Hansa, and Father
all tried to draw me from my bed, sure that
a measure of festival fun would go a long
way toward cheering me up.
But song and dance cannot close a wound like
that. More like it pours salt on it—watching
other people sing and dance like nothing had
happened, all the while blistered with grief.
I didn’t go. Not that year nor the next.
I’d tried to spend the time reading Tante
Hansa’s spell books—the only thing that’d
kept me sane in those days—but even that
took too much effort. All the strength I had
went to shutting out laughter and song.
It was only last year that I agreed to go
with Nik again.
He’d lost his friend too but had to make
a show of being at the festival immediately—the
day of her death—duty and title forcing
him to walk around in his nice clothes and
accept the people’s offerings to Urda. He
didn’t have to speak as he does yet again
tonight, but it was still painful enough just
to stand up in front of everyone while so
broken.
We are far from that now—not healed, of
course, but with just two days left, this
festival has felt like the last one we attended
when Anna was alive. Iker came that year,
arriving with his parents from Rigeby Bay,
fourteen and suddenly very tall. Anna and
I mooned over him every night, whispering
about his eyes and laughing while huddled
up in her mansion bedroom. It would be a year
before she told me that she actually preferred
Nik to Iker and my mind filled of dreams of
us as twin queens, the friherrinde-to-princess
and the pauper-to-princess loves of Øldenburg
kings on both sides of the Øresund Strait.
Of course, Annemette is not Anna, but I can’t
shake the feeling that this is what we could
have had. I glance over at Annemette as she
watches Nik speak on the platform in front
of the bonfire. Rosebud lips slightly parted,
she follows his words with the precision of
a predator, so intent on remembering everything
he says. I never saw Anna look at Nik like
Annemette does, but eleven-year-old girls
can hide their feelings as much as any of
us.
Suddenly, Annemette’s lips pull up in a
smile, eyes sharpening to something hard,
and I follow her gaze up to Nik. He’s watching
her back, but then looks to me, doing his
best to concentrate on the words. Still, his
ears begin to blush. Then Iker hands Nik the
ceremonial first loaf of bread—large as
a cannonball, crafted of dark rye, and braided
in the shape of the sun wheel. Nik holds the
loaf above his head.
“And so, let us give thanks to Urda with
the staff of life—bread. Let us share our
gifts of grain with our neighbors. Let no
person in need go without. Let the loaves
fly to them with the gentlest of care, a blessing
from Urda by way of a neighbor’s hand.”
Nik tears a hunk of bread off the loaf and
hands it to King Asger. Another piece goes
to Queen Charlotte, and a third to Iker, whose
parents stayed home this year. Together, the
royal family lines up in front of the fire,
bread in hand.
Nik lifts his piece above his crowned head.
“Let the sharing begin.”
With that, all four of them toss the bread
in the direction of the crowd. Nik’s lands
gently in Annemette’s lap. She laughs, and
I’m so busy laughing too that I’m not
paying attention when a crusty hunk of rye
thwacks me square in the chest, bouncing off
my bodice and into my lap. I glance up and
see Iker with a vicious grin, hovering over
the royal table, snatching more.
I grab a loaf from the table next to me and
stand. I rip it in half and give the remainder
to Annemette. “Aim for Iker.”
Her brows pull together with a moment of confusion.
“I thought the bread was for the less fortunate?”
I gesture toward the sky. “It’s raining
bread. No one will go hungry, I promise.”
Annemette looks up to see that, yes, bread
of every make and shape is flying through
the air. She ducks as a sweet roll screams
in from Malvina’s direction. It bounces
off Fru Ulla with a honeyed thud before a
toddler snags it with two chubby hands.
“It’s all in good fun,” I assure her,
and chuck the bread Iker’s way. He puts
his arms up to shield his face but drops them
too quickly and gets clobbered right in the
nose by Annemette’s piece.
This only serves to make him grin and seize
two cherry tarts from the table. He thrusts
one into Nik’s hands, and they advance on
us, eyes glinting.
“Run!” I screech, and grab Annemette’s
hand.
We snake through the crowd and onto an open
stretch of beach. Twined together, we run
along the shoreline. But the boys are faster,
and tarts whack us each in the back. We fall
to the sand in hysterics—something I haven’t
done in four years.
The boys pull us up—Iker hooking one arm
under my knees and the other at my shoulders.
He runs a finger along my back until my once
class-defying gown is slick with beach-ruined
cherry filling and aims it toward my mouth.
“Sandy tart for the lady.”
I seal my lips and shake my head.
“For Urda, you must.”
The absurdity of the look on his face pulls
my lips apart, and he seizes his opportunity
to drop the filling onto my tongue. I gag
and buck, coughing with laughter, and tumble
out of his arms and into the sand.
Iker goes down too, landing beside me. His
eyes seem to glow as he leans over my body
and lowers his lips to mine. I enjoy the kiss,
his newly shaven skin baby soft against my
chin. I guess Iker doesn’t defy all royal
protocols; Queen Charlotte won this round.
“Mmmm,” he says, licking cherry filling
from his lips. “Delicious, though a bit
. . . gritty.”
I laugh. “Sandy tarts always are.”
“Odd bit of cuisine, you Havnestaders.”
“Eat up. Nik will expect you at full strength
tomorrow,” I say.
Iker raises a brow, mischief on his lips.
“What if I told him I was saving my strength
for you?”
I push him away from me and stand, my back
to him, arms crossed.
“I was kidding,” he pleads. “Are all
the games tomorrow?”
I nod, dusting myself off while he still lies
in the sand.
“Does this mean tomorrow is when you will
shimmy across a log?”
When I don’t respond, he stands and wraps
his arms around me from behind, trailing two
fingers across my navel, having them mimic
a stiff jog.
“As promised, my prince,” I say, laughing
a little. Why do I always give in?
“Yes—”
A scream cuts off Iker’s answer. Annemette.
Both Iker and I whip our heads toward Annemette
and Nik. They are closer to the crowd, Annemette
crouching in the sand, Nik staggering a bit
before falling to his knees, clutching his
stomach. Standing before both of them is Malvina,
hands in front of her body as if they’d
just released a dagger.
Iker stiffens, his whole body suddenly rigid
with tension. “Cousin?”
Nik staggers to a stand and raises a hand
to wave him off, turning toward us. His white
shirt and dazzling royal coat are a mess of
black, like the tears I’ve cried twice before.
Iker takes a step toward the scene, fists
forming.
But then Nik points toward his boots. Toward
the pie plate lying facedown in the sand.
“Urda has been quite generous with Malvina’s
blueberry pie. The goddess must have decided
that my wardrobe and the beach were in particular
need of nourishment.” With that, Nik begins
to laugh.
Immediately, Iker joins him, and I catch Annemette’s
eye as she rises from her crouch. A little
chuckle bubbles from her lips, growing into
a full laugh when her attention turns to Nik’s
doubled-over form. I’m almost too shocked
to laugh, having been holding my breath this
whole time, but then I join in too.
The only one not finding humor in all this
is Malvina, embarrassment but not regret in
the set of her jaw. She doesn’t apologize
as she storms past Annemette—clearly her
intended target—and snatches the pie plate
from the sand at Nik’s feet.
She stands to face him. Nik attempts to compose
himself enough to look her in the eye but
fails miserably, laughter still wryly present
in his features as he lets the blueberry glop
and sugar crust slide off his gold-threaded
coat and onto the beach.
“I hope you will enjoy this gift in the
name of Urda,” Malvina announces, nose in
the air, before pivoting on her heel as best
as she can in beach sand, blond hair flying.
When she’s gone, we gather around him and
survey the damage. The shirt, coat and even
his pants are all unsalvageable.
But true to his nature, Nik just grins and
presents his sopping clothes.
“Pie, ladies? Urda does insist.”
I WAKE WITH THE SUN THE FOLLOWING MORNING,
STILL warm with feelings of belonging from
the night before. Yesterday was a daydream
from start to end, and I wanted to never wake
up. But in the white morning light, reality
becomes stark and my mood shifts quickly.
Annemette is still fast asleep, toes stretching
toward the ceiling, arms thrown above her
head, tangled within her waves. I lie there
for a moment and listen to the gulls before
I realize my opportunity. I know a way I can
do some real good today.
On silent feet, I head to the wardrobe and
tug it open. The first dress on the right
is one I wore two days ago when I met Annemette.
I can’t believe that’s all the time that’s
passed, but in the same breath, I can’t
believe so much of our time has vanished.
Today and tomorrow until midnight, and then
it could all be over in the most horrific
way possible—or it might be the happiest
ending of all.
Annemette still seems confident, and I’m
obeying her request that I not intervene,
at least not magically, but the thought of
losing another friend to the sea is almost
unbearable. First Anna, then nearly Nik, and
now Annemette, who’s only been in my life
for a short while, but who’s helped open
my world in ways I’d never imagined. She’s
the friend Anna never could be to me, that
Nik can’t be, either. She’s the only one
who knows my secrets. Well, most of them.
I’ve been pushing these feelings down, telling
myself this is her decision, that I should
instead try to appreciate the life around
me, as I’m sure she is, but I don’t know
how much longer I can feel so helpless.
At least I can still use my magic for one
thing. I fish through my dress pocket. My
fingers brush past the vial of ink from the
other day and curl around the little amethyst,
safe and sound where I left it. I can only
hope that my morning away from the docks led
to just one day of poor fishing, or maybe
none at all—the magic is new enough that
I don’t know what happens if I don’t do
it.
I dress quickly, and, minutes later, I make
it to the docks without seeing a soul. The
cobblestones are littered with dew-covered
crumbs, orphaned the night before, and so
far neglected by the Øresund birds.
The docks are quiet too, no ships coming or
going, though that will change in a few hours.
Today is the favorite among the festivalgoers.
The gluttony of the previous nights draws
some, the final day of sailing and dancing
attracts others, but not nearly as many as
those lining up to participate or watch the
games today.
Our games aren’t exactly as sophisticated
as the ancient Olympics Fru Seraphine taught
us about in school, but they are more than
enough for the people of Havnestad.
Palm out and full, I close my eyes and run
the amethyst along the docked ship hulls one
by one, mumbling aloud the words that seem
to work, mostly because, with no one around,
I don’t have to say them in my head.
“Knorr yfir haf, knorr yfir haf, sigla tryggr,
fanga þrír.
Knorr yfir haf, knorr yfir haf, sigla tryggr,
fanga þrír.”
The words hit my ear as childish, so much
more sophisticated when spoken only in the
space of my mind. I suddenly wish I’d trusted
my magic enough to create a simple and strong
Old Norse command—like something Annemette
would do. I’d do it now but I’m afraid
of what the change will bring.
My words are like a nursery rhyme—but they
will do.
When I’m finished with every ship in port,
I stand on the edge of the royal dock—the
longest pier in Havnestad Harbor—and face
the strait.
“Urda, if you will, bring my words to Father,
wherever in the Øresund he may be. Keep him
safe; leave him to me. You do not need him.
Please don’t take him simply because you
can.”
Anna’s face crosses my mind, open and free
with laughter before she was taken by the
waves. But I push it down as far as it will
go, along with my dark thoughts of the morning.
I need to live like Annemette, like Iker,
and enjoy the day to its fullest.
I turn and head back to the castle.
I don’t see him at first, my eyes on the
clouds the sun has tinged pink with the rising
dawn. But then I hear the soft plink of a
guitaren being strummed ever so lightly in
the tulip garden. That song again, from the
party.
“Nik?” His chin tilts my way, eyes swinging
away from the sea. He is on the stone bench
under the shade tree, the wrinkled version
of his strapping statue across the garden—muslin
nightclothes rumpled, unbrushed hair shoved
out of his eyes with his fingertips. “Did
you come out here this morning to let the
birds clean the last bit of pie from behind
your ears?”
“I ran a bath last night, but thanks for
noticing.”
“Then you must have risen early to meditate
on a plan to best Iker in the rock carry.”
Nik raises an arm and pats his lean bicep.
“The only plan I need, my lady.”
I punch him on the arm, and we sit quietly
for a few moments. The pink of dawn has shifted
to salmon, the tone already rumbling toward
the golden yellow it turns just before the
classic blue sky wins out and the sun is fully
over the horizon.
Fingers scrabble Nik’s hair back again from
his brow, and his face turns toward the stones
at our feet. After a breath, he raises his
eyes to mine, and I have a feeling I might
learn the real answer to his morning meditation.
“Evie . . . ,” he starts, and my heart
sinks at the mournful tone. Oh no. “Evie,
have you really kissed Iker?”
My heart skids to a halt and I sit there,
jaw tense. I don’t know what to say. I’m
not ready to talk about me and Iker. Not to
Nik, anyway.
I laugh and elbow him in the ribs, hoping
a joke can mend whatever is in his voice.
“The real question is, have you kissed Annemette?”
I hope he’ll turn red. Say yes. Admit to
it so that maybe Annemette has a chance to
stay—to live!—and fill the hole in our
hearts.
Instead, his face squishes up as if he’s
smelled something spoiled. “Of course not.
I’m a romantic, but I’m not a cad—I’m
not, not . . .”
“Iker?” My voice is angrier than I intended,
but there’s something in the pit of my stomach.
Something hot like disappointment, not only
at him for his clear disdain for Iker but
for anything I do with him.
He stops and starts, and I can tell he doesn’t
know where to begin. It’s rare that I ever
get angry with him. Rare that he can’t bring
order with a princely smile or a knowing glance,
his only tools of conflict the royal formalities
his mother has ingrained in him.
“I realize it’s stupid,” he says finally.
“I’m sixteen and a prince to boot—I
should be having fun. Mother would never let
something wrongheaded get so far along. She
has plans for me, besides. It’s just . . . I
like Annemette. But it’s not . . . it’s
not”—he looks at me, and there’s something
else in his eyes—“as it is in the storybooks.”
Then he glances up at me, the change in his
focus clear in the set of his jaw. “And
for him to kiss you . . .” Nik shakes his
head, his posture withering. “God, I must
sound a mess—”
“No,” I say, air rushing into my lungs
just enough to get the word out.
He laughs softly under his breath. “Yes,
I do. I sound crazed.”
“You sound confused. You can find ‘crazed’
in those lovesick books we read as children.
Those princes who lock girls up in a tower
to get their way—those are the crazy ones.”
Nik nods to himself. “Yes, Mette is a nice
girl, lovely really, and beautiful, and I
regret that she’ll have to return to Odense,
but I don’t think I’ll ever love her enough
to be . . . to be . . . her fairy-tale prince.”
My stomach practically collapses. But Nik
is just speaking from the heart. He doesn’t
know there is no Odense for Annemette. No
. . . nothing. She’s just another girl his
mother has forced upon him. What if I told
him the truth? Maybe that would change things.
Evie, what are you talking about? Tell him
she’s a mermaid? But maybe he’d see how
wonderful she is and would want to save her,
just like he tried to save Anna. But then
this truly would all be on his shoulders.
All that guilt. Can love spring from guilt?
Is that true love? I don’t know . . . how
should I know what true love is? No, if I
told him the truth, it might ruin any further
time she has to win him over. This is all
my fault, for trouncing around with Iker while
Nik spends precious time worrying about me,
taking his mind off Annemette. I have to try
something else.
“She reminds me so much of Anna . . . ,” I
say, feeling as if the words are tiptoeing
out.
“Her coloring, yes,” he admits, but doesn’t
go further. Not the response I was hoping
for.
“And her features. Her singing voice.”
He shrugs and leans back off his knees and
straightens. “But you know what’s not?
The way she looks at me—Anna never would’ve
allowed herself to think of me as handsome.”
“That’s so untrue! She had a huge crush
on you, and you know it.” I knock his shoulder,
though it feels strange to speak of Anna’s
private feelings as a joke. I’m quiet for
a moment, and then I say, “Give Annemette
a real chance, please. For me.”
“But what about you and Iker?”
“Stop thinking about Iker, Nik! I’m happy,
but I won’t let him ruin me, like I know
you’re so afraid of. I’m smarter than
that.” He blushes red for a moment, but
I keep going. “The only happiness I want
you to worry about is yours.”
FOUR YEARS BEFORE
The boy dove back in. He couldn’t just leave
it to these other men to find his friend.
He’d saved one; he needed to try to save
the other.
Drowning was common in Havnestad—the sea
took as much as she gave—but this, this
could not be.
Immediately, the water clawed at the damp
length of him, the undertow a thousand hands
ripping his body toward the swirling sands
below.
His father’s constant refrain crept into
his head. Do not be a hero, Iker; you are
already a prince.
He’d said it anytime Nik had done anything
particularly reckless. A compliment swaddled
in a reminder: You are not just a prince,
you are an heir. The lone heir.
And here was his father’s voice, nagging
as fiercely as the waves.
He crested the surface and shook it all off—the
words, the water—and filled his lungs. All
around him, men thrashed in the waves. Not
a single one held Anna.
The boy dove down again, forcing his eyes
open against the salty sting.
Blue. Blue everywhere.
He blinked, letting his vision adjust.
Shadows on the ocean floor became crops of
seaweed, moving in dark time. Algae, debris,
and the tiniest of sea horses floated across
the blue, a mosaic rather than one solidly
flowing body.
His eyes swung left, right. His entire body
spun around.
She’s here. She’s here. She must be here.
He surfaced again, not far from the sandbar
now. No men yelling. No one sagging under
the weight of a blonde in a petticoat.
Back down again, deeper, deeper, the undertow
greedily guiding him on.
Eyes open, he scanned the bottom. Lungs burning
for breath, he dove.
And there.
One hundred yards away. Down in a crevice.
A flash of white. A foot, bare against a huge
tangle of seaweed and coral.
Eyes pinned on her location, he shot to the
surface—he’d need air to get her. Eight
great, heaving breaths.
I can do this. I can get to her.
Down he dove again, eyes open as he plunged,
pinned to the sliver of white. So far away.
So far down.
The boy’s lungs burned. His ears popped.
Darkness crept into the corners of his vision.
And still the slip of white was there. But
not getting closer. It never seemed to get
any larger, any more attainable. It just flashed
on the seafloor, so much a star he could not
touch.
His mind began to slow, as did his legs and
arms, which no longer struggled against the
undertow.
You do not need to be a hero, Iker; you are
already a prince.
You are not just a prince, you are an heir.
The lone heir.
Breath beating against his lungs, he made
his choice.
The prince pushed himself deeper.
His life didn’t matter more than hers. He
was the one with the chance to save her, and
that chance shouldn’t hinge on the blood
in his veins.
Legs burning, he kicked, no breath left in
his lungs to propel him. But he was so close.
He could make out actual toes now. Head pounding
without air, blood spiked with pressure, he
kicked again, his arms pulling against the
water.
But then came a pressure on his foot. Yanking
him back—up. Pulling him until, for a heartbeat,
the weight was gone. As soon as it disappeared,
it was replaced with elbows hooking under
his shoulders. A chest at his back. And force,
so much force, propelling him to the surface.
In that moment, his lungs finally sputtered
for breath and he involuntarily inhaled, water
still surrounding him. A deep mouthful of
the sea hovered above his windpipe for a split
second before he spit it back into the water.
Out of breath, out of time, water closing
in, he broke the surface. The air was so fresh
it burned; as his lungs heaved, his tongue
swelled from the salt he’d inhaled.
Coughing, breathing—finally breathing—he
opened his eyes again, water streaming into
his eyes.
He couldn’t see well, but he knew the face
before him.
“No! Iker—” he began, coughing. Coughing
so hard. More salt water streamed out of his
mouth. Dribbled down his chin. He wiped at
his mouth with a sleeve so wet, it just smeared
the water around with more water.
“I’ve got you, Cousin. I’ve got you.
Don’t worry. You’re safe.”
“I—” He coughed again and took a breath,
long and deep. “I have to get her.”
With air in his lungs, he tried to shrug off
his cousin.
“She’s gone, Nik. She’s gone. And you
were going to be too.”
“No! She’s down there. I saw her. You
had to have seen her too. She’s right there,
right down—”
“Don’t be a hero, Nik.” Boat-strong
biceps pinned the prince in a hug—his arms
stuck at his sides, his only recourse to kick,
but that just propelled them closer to the
beach. Farther from her.
“Iker, please. She needs us. Anna needs
us. We can rescue her. We can—”
“We can’t.” His cousin’s newly deepened
voice cracked as he said it, and there was
a hitch in his kick. “We can’t.”
“We can! We can get her!” He was yelling,
even though his voice was rough and sloppy.
His cousin only squeezed harder. His lips
came to the prince’s ear, his voice smaller
than seemed possible. “If you die rescuing
her, it won’t give solace to your parents
or your people. It will only give Havnestad
another body.”
“But she’s not a body. She’s not. She’s
there. Right there.” But even as he said
the words, he knew it had been too long now.
Ten minutes, though it felt like a hundred.
And then he started to cry. Salty tears running
down his cheeks and into the harbor. He didn’t
wipe them. He let them run. Let them join
Anna at sea.
THE ANNUAL LITHASBLOT GAMES BEGIN IN THE SWELTER
of noon. Havnestad citizens and onlookers
from across the Øresund Strait spill onto
the main beach, ready for games of skill and
sport to take place from the mountains above
to the seas below.
It’s the first time in days the boys aren’t
properly gussied up in public. To be sure,
they’re both clean-shaven—the easier to
show off their game faces—but they are also
wearing simple cotton work pants and shirts
rolled at the sleeves. This change of dress
is tradition too.
Today is about demonstrating skill. I wasn’t
lying when I told Iker our games were useful—they
were indeed born out of utility. Rock climbing
and trail running in the mountains. Log running
in the stream that feeds into the harbor.
Swimming in the mouth of the sea. Vital to
life, every one of them. Useful—right down
to the rock carry along the beach, which mimics
laboring to bring cargo ashore.
And each citizen in Havnestad has an equal
shot to compete. Be you ninety-five or still
flush with baby fat, if you can walk, you
are allowed to have a go—with the royal
family cheering you on, or possibly acting
as your competition.
After plates of samsø, rye bread, and peaches,
Nik is instructed by his father to oversee
the mountain events first. Those sports have
the fewest competitors, and King Asger would
much rather view the action on the beach.
And King Asger gets what King Asger wants—even
from his son.
True to his nature, Nik bows—no crown atop
his head—before grabbing another peach and
a flask of water and tugging Annemette toward
Lille Bjerg Pass.
I side-eye Iker when he doesn’t make a move
to follow.
His strong hand gently cuffs my wrist and
pulls me close. In a breath, I’m an inch
away from his lips. The depths of his eyes
are striking in the high sun, clear and merry
after a good night’s rest in a real bed
and not a ship’s dank quarters. “Let’s
just stay here alone.”
I shift my eyes to the beach. “Alone—with
five thousand of our closest friends, including
your aunt and uncle.”
Iker laughs and gently fingers the curls that
have blown forward over my shoulder. “So
many people that not a one of them is watching
. . .”
No, they’re watching. I can feel it. He’s
just used to it.
I pull away, shifting the arm he’s snagged
so I’m grabbing his wrist as he clutches
mine. I tug him toward Lille Bjerg Pass. “There
are many side trails along the pass, thick
with brush.”
He raises a brow and finally takes a step
forward. “It would be a shame if we were
to get lost.”
“Such a shame. Nik would be so disappointed.”
“Only if he’s lost in the same brush we
are.”
It’s true. Nik returned a different person
after our early morning conversation, focusing
on Annemette with a renewed intensity.
With tangled hands, we march up Market Street.
We are several lengths behind Annemette and
Nik, though they are moving at a snail’s
pace—Annemette has yet to see much of the
town outside of the festival, and she’s
poking in every doorway and picture window
to see the wares. The sweetshop man already
handed her a lollipop, which proceeded to
turn her tongue a grisly shade of red. She
dared to show us a block back, sticking out
her tongue nearly down to her chin. It was
quite the picture, a bloody maw beneath the
face of an angel. Of course, she thought it
was the funniest thing. I thanked Urda that
Malvina wasn’t around to see it.
Nik laughed too, endearment written all over
his face. He has no idea how far she’s traveled
to see these things we walk past every day,
to stroll down the street with him.
“I have been to Odense,” Iker starts,
sun lines crinkling around his eyes, “and
it isn’t Copenhagen, but it isn’t a one-horse
village either. By the way she responded to
the sucker, you’d suppose she’d never
had a candy in all her life.”
“Showing delight isn’t a crime, Iker.”
And it isn’t, though I know that answer
won’t atone for Annemette’s fierce sense
of wonder. Thus, I turn it back on him. “Not
everyone is as difficult to amuse as the salt-worn
prince of Rigeby Bay.”
His lips turn up and his eyes flash my way.
“I laugh deeper than anyone and you know
it—whether I’ve lived on only salt herring
for three weeks or not.” His fingers squeeze
mine and I kiss his shoulder. “What I mean
is, there’s just something unnatural about
her level of delight.”
My heart starts to pound and my temples grow
hot. This line of thought is no good. No good
at all. I change tactics.
“Imagine it her way.” I sweep my free
hand out in front of him. “She arrived at
Havnestad with a chaperone green with illness,
knowing not a single other soul. And despite
it all, she’s been taken in, given a bed
in a beautiful palace, and the dashing prince
she’s come to meet clearly believes her
to be something special.” I swing up our
tangled hands so they’re within view. “That
is a whirlwind of delight, is it not? The
curl was nearly blown out of my hair just
by being a bystander.”
He gives me a courtesy laugh and snags a wayward
lock of hair with his free hand, tugging it
completely smooth. He lets it go and watches
as it bounces back into a spiral. “That
would’ve been disastrous. Even the salons
of Paris would not have been able to reproduce
these.”
My cheeks run scarlet as we reach the end
of the cobblestones and the trailhead of Lille
Bjerg Pass. Annemette and Nik have already
disappeared around a bend. I step in front
of Iker onto the single track, and our hands
drop.
“I’m just saying,” he says, “what
do we know about Annemette? How do we know
she is who she says she is?”
I laugh, trying to make it seem as if he’s
being ridiculous, and not appropriately concerned.
“What, do you think she’s some con artist
on the run, stealing crown jewels one Lithasblot
at a time?” It’s the most absurd thing
I can offer, except for the truth.
“No. No. She’s a sweet girl . . . there’s
just something about her I can’t put my
finger on. And I don’t like that feeling—especially
when it involves family.”
“I know what it is,” I say, hoping to
finally put this to rest—for Annemette as
much as for myself. “She looks like Anna.”
His step hesitates behind me. “Your friend
who drowned?”
“The very one.”
“Sure. She had blond hair.”
“Yes. And blue eyes. And creamy skin. A
heart-shaped face—all of it. The resemblance
about bowled me over.” And I can’t help
it: tears well in my eyes. “I’d thought
I’d seen a ghost.”
He stops moving forward. I turn around and
he’s watching me, brows pulled together
and serious. It’s just as he was on the
balcony, suspicion slinking across his skin
as fierce as the sunlight.
“Are you sure there’s no way this girl
could have known that? Picked the name Annemette
on purpose? She could be preying on the both
of you—using your memories against you.”
The slope of the trail puts us face-to-face,
and he presses his thumbs to the corners of
my eyes, wiping away the tears that have welled.
I place my hand on his chest. “Who are these
scoundrels you meet on the high seas? Does
anyone in the world really do such awful things?
Do you not have any faith in your fellow man?”
“Evelyn, I am aware that you are not naïve,
but I feel as if I should remind both you
and my cousin that people aren’t always
who they say they are.”
“You’re not wrong.” I take a step toward
him and touch my forehead to his, our lips
a breath away, our eyes locked. “And while
I find your concern incredibly endearing,
I’m through talking about this. Annemette
may not be Anna, but she is my friend. I have
not been duped.”
I close the distance between us, our lips
meeting. He sinks deeply into me, hands wrapping
around my back, fingers in my hair. We stand
like that for several moments, but it isn’t
until he’s so taken he closes his eyes that
I know I’ve finally won this round.
“Taking the long way up the mountain?”
I push away from Iker and see Annemette standing
a few feet from us, Nik surely around the
bend. Her brow is raised, but there’s a
smirk on her black cherry–stained mouth.
“Haven’t you heard? I’m never on time.”
He grins a bit at his own self-effacing jab,
but I swear I still see a skeptical look in
his eyes as he stalks past her.
Annemette grabs my hands, and we both burst
out laughing. It really does feel like Anna
is here.
We make our way up to the games, but by the
time we reach them, Nik and Iker have already
been plied into competing in the mountain
run portion of the games. Royal duty and gamesmanship
mean Annemette and I have been left behind
to hold court on a fallen log. Normally, I’d
run too—I’m swifter than I look—but
Annemette’s feet are already bothering her,
the burning she felt yesterday more painful
than before. Instead, we’ll watch the rock
climbers from afar while waiting for the boys
to rumble back down the mountain, sweaty,
dusty, and full of new tales.
“How do you do it?” she asks quietly.
“What do you mean?” I reply.
“Get Iker to kiss you like that?” she
says with more than a hint of exasperation
lining her voice. “It’s silly, but I was
watching you—”
“For tips?” I want to laugh—the idea
of someone watching me for my alluring abilities
is ridiculous, and I still have my doubts
about whether there’s actually any love
behind Iker’s kisses, but Annemette seems
so desperate. She is desperate.
Annemette’s cheeks flush, though the pink
is tempered by the mountain light. “I’ve
done everything I can to show him how I feel,
and still no kiss! But I do think he likes
me.”
“He does. I know he does!” I push this
morning out of my mind entirely. Nik has heeded
my words. I know it. It’s going to be all
right.
She is quiet for a second, her features mellowing
with thought. “My father, the sea king,
says that when everything is as you hoped,
you are blind to the imperfections.”
Somehow, I’m stunned silent that the sea
king in our childhood tales is as real as
the mermaid before me. Finally, I nod. “Your
father is wise.”
“But I’m not blind. His wise words ring
in my ears when I should be enjoying every
moment. Instead, I look past the perfect couple
we are on the outside and see all the reasons
why Nik isn’t in love with me.”
“I know what you mean,” I say.
“No, Iker loves you.”
I shake my head. “I would like Iker to love
me. But Iker has a reputation for kissing
any girl whose knees go weak at the sight
of him—and I’m not the only one in the
Øresund Kingdoms with trouble standing. Iker
and I are not forever, and I’m trying to
be all right with that.”
She looks at her feet. “So, he has other
girls he treats like you?”
“Yes. Or he did. I don’t know.” I can
feel my face flushing. “The point is, Nik
does not! There is only one fish in his sea
and it is you . . .”
“That is a ridiculous analogy, Evie.”
“And here I thought it was clever, given
your situation.”
Annemette squeezes her eyes shut, and I regret
making a stupid joke at a time like this.
“My situation. Yes.” She huffs out a sad
little laugh. “Such a situation—love at
first sight with a boy who won’t even kiss
me. I was so sure he was going to lead to
a lifetime of happiness, not . . .”
Neither of us wants to say what her life will
be otherwise.
WHEN NIK AND IKER RETURN, THEY ARE EAGER TO
prove who is the strongest, the fastest, the
most agile, their egos sorely bruised after
both losing the mountain run. It seems the
tailor’s son, little Johan Olsen, is not
so little anymore.
“I’ve never seen someone run like him,”
Nik admits as we make our way over to the
Havnestad River, which slices through the
mountains before emptying to the sea. “It
was a sight to see.”
“You want to see a sight?” says Iker.
“Challenge me to a log run, Cousin. I could
beat ten of that Olsen boy, and you, too.”
I look over at Annemette, who has plastered
a smile on her face and is laughing along
with the boys. And, because I’d love to
see Iker dunked in the Havnestad River, I
am totally encouraging it too.
Nik chuckles—a royal chuckle, but an actual
chuckle nonetheless. As we reach the riverbank,
he’s still contemplating. He props one foot
up on the tail end of the right log. There’s
an open one to his left, ready for Iker.
“If I’m not mistaken,” Nik says, “I
heard you came to this Lithasblot extravaganza
with the promise of a certain raven-haired
girl scampering across a log, and it wasn’t
me, Cousin.”
Nik! How could he? But I laugh an Iker laugh,
head thrown toward the sky. Nik is losing
it too—chortling so hard that his foot has
slipped off the end of the log and he’s
nearly squatted to a sit on the thing.
Annemette, though, has her wits about her.
I right myself just as she glances my way
with a wicked little grin and a gleam in her
eyes. “How about this compromise? Nik and
Evie race. The winner faces Iker.”
Iker’s brows climb his forehead and his
eyes sparkle, clear and thrilled. He claps
his big, strong hands together. “Yes. That’s
it. The lady has the perfect idea!”
I shake my head. “Yes, the perfect idea
to keep herself dry.”
Annemette shrugs and backs into the small
crowd that has gathered, lined along the rocks
and logs. “I’m just a spectator.”
Nik laughs and manages a long lunge to nudge
her sweetly with his elbow. “That’s what
I thought, too, my dear, and now look where
it’s got me.”
I cock a brow at him. “Yes, as my first
victim.”
“Hey, now, what makes you so sure you’ll
win?” Nik says to me, a smile playing at
his lips, though his tone is attempting to
sound indignant.
“Sometimes you just have a feeling, my prince.
You’re sure to be a loser, Asger Niklas
Bryniulf Øldenburg III.”
As the spectators and competitors chant Nik’s
name, he plants a foot on the log across from
me. Both logs are suspended just above the
current, tied by ship ropes on either side
to keep them straight and somewhat steady—to
keep the competition fair, not to create ease.
It is twenty-five feet from one end to the
other. We must race to the other side, touch
the bank, and then make a return trip. The
first one back or the one to stay out of the
water wins. If we both wind up in the river,
then it’s a draw, no matter who fell first.
Our classmate, Ruyven Van Horn, squashed ginger
hair, elephant ears and all, is there between
us, the official start on his lips. “On
your marks . . . get set . . . go!”
We lunge onto the logs. Nik’s legs are much
longer, and he’s ahead after a step, but
his center of gravity is much higher, and
he immediately wobbles.
“Unsteady so soon, Cousin?” Iker laughs
in the background.
I can’t see him, but I’m sure Nik is smiling
right back. “Jeer me, and you only serve
to anger me.”
In the time it’s taken him to steady himself
and answer Iker’s ribbing, I’ve already
made it five steps. The logs are slicked over,
but mine is the perfect size for my feet.
Planting each foot in a turnout à la the
French ballet, I can move quickly to the center
point with shallow steps. Beside me, Nik hasn’t
altered his stride, daring gravity to take
him with every long step, but using his strength
and coordination to stay steady.
I make it to the end of my log and tag the
ground on the other side, earning me a flag
raise from Ruyven’s counterpart.
“Excellent, Evie!” Annemette cheers.
I get both feet back onto my log just as Nik
lunges off the end of his and safely into
the dirt.
“Mette, you traitor,” Nik yells, mounting
his log a bit too quickly. His arms windmill
through my periphery in a grand arc—the
crowd gasps.
“Less jawing, more movement, Cousin. Evie’s
smoking you!”
“You only root for me because you’re stupid
enough to think you can beat me in the next
round. Against her you won’t have a chance,
and you know it.”
I’m still in the lead but just barely, my
steps slower and more careful now. Over the
years, I’ve seen many a competitor fall
in the river a yard from the finish because
his mind was already on land. I could easily
whisper one of Tante Hansa’s spells and
dry the log without any notice, but I won’t
do that. I’m not a cheat. So my heart stills
as I concentrate on the log before me, the
sound of rushing water the only thing in my
ears.
Nik is beside me, but my tunnel vision has
drowned him out—if his arms are flailing
or if he is steady and slowing too, I don’t
know. All I know is that when I touch dirt,
Ruyven raises my arm, and when I look over,
Nik is there too, hands on his hips, breathing
at a good clip.
“The lady, by an inch!” Ruyven says. Annemette
is clapping and Iker, too, though his game
face is already sliding into place. The rest
of the crowd is mostly silent until Nik raises
his hands above his head in thanks—then
they go wild.
“Well done, Evie.” Nik squeezes my shoulder.
Then he leans in, for my ears only. “Ignore
them. They only cheer because they have to.”
Then, to the crowd, he says, “Let’s hear
it for Evie!”
Slightly heartier applause chases his exclamation,
but—not shockingly—also some boos. And
then all eyes swing to Iker. His gaze is locked
on my face, the glee in the blue of his eyes
already hardening to concentration. If Iker
competes in the grand way that he does everything
else, I’m going to need much more than an
inch.
I turn and place my foot on the log.
“Are you sure you’re ready to exert yourself
again so quickly, Evelyn?”
“Quit stalling, Romeo. Let’s go.”
I glance over to Ruyven, who is having a fine
time laughing at our expense. Ruyven meets
my eyes, his normally dough-pale face now
plum red, and raises his flag for a start.
Iker is still a step or two away from his
log, turned around, playing to the crowd.
I settle my footing, calf muscles tense beneath
my dress.
“On your marks . . .” It takes Iker almost
a second too long to register the words. Ruyven
is onto the next part before the crown prince
of Rigeby Bay has time to turn. “Get set
. . .” Iker is a yard from his log. “Go!”
I dash onto my log, keeping my chest low,
hips square and knees bent. I’m five feet
in front when Iker finally mounts his log,
but in true Iker form, he takes the lead with
just two grand steps.
The surrounding wood is alive with voices,
so strong that they rise above my concentration
and the babbling of the stream—Iker is always
one to bring out the rowdiness in any situation.
“Go get him!” Annemette yells.
“You’ve got this, Evie!” Nik cheers.
But I don’t have it. Iker is already a yard
from touching down on the other side of the
log, his bold steps risky but not without
reward. I am still at least ten careful steps
from the bank and the chance to turn around.
When Iker’s feet hit the dirt, he immediately
spins and points to the flagman on the other
side and then raises his arms, grand and proud
as he addresses the crowd.
“Will no one cheer for the first-place horse?
Am I so hideous?”
At this, every girl in the crowd, save Annemette,
screams his name.